<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../../../schema/current/translation.rng" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
            <fileDesc>
                <titleStmt>
                    <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="en">Chapter 5: On Leather</title>
                    <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Sa-Ltn">Carmavastu</title>
                    <title type="mainTitle" xml:lang="Bo-Ltn">ko lpags kyi gzhi/</title>
                    <author role="translatorMain" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-1">Lochung Translation Committee</author>
                    <consultant role="projectManager" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-2">Cuilan Liu</consultant>
                    <author role="translatorEng" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-3">Cuilan Liu</author>
                    <author role="translatorEng" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-4">Susan Roach</author>
                    <author role="translatorEng" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-5">Andy Francis</author>
                    <author role="translatorEng" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-6">Jamyang Rinchen</author>
                    <editor role="projectEditor" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-21">Robert Miller</editor>
                </titleStmt>
                <editionStmt>
                    <edition>v 0.0.10 <date>2025</date>
                    </edition>
                </editionStmt>
                <publicationStmt>
                    <availability status="2.d"/>
                    <idno xml:id="UT22084-001-005"/>
                    <date/>
                </publicationStmt>
                <sourceDesc>
                    <bibl key="toh1-5" type="chapter">
                        <ref>Toh 1-5</ref>
                        <biblScope>vol:1,ff.251r-277v(pp.502-554)</biblScope>
                        <location work="UT4CZ5369" count-pages="53">
                            <volume number="1" start-page="502" end-page="554"/>
                        </location>
                        <idno parent-id="O1JC114941JC11497" work="http://read.84000.co/sections"/>
                        <idno source-id="O1JC114941JC12909" work="W22084"/>
                    </bibl>
                </sourceDesc>
                <notesStmt/>
                <revisionDesc>
                    <change who="#admin" when="2019-12-20T12:56:48.575Z" type="text-version" status="v 0.0.1" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-7">
                        <desc>Automated version increment</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-03-07T11:14:31.388Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.2" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-8">
                        <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-08-08T09:44:14.428Z" type="translation-status" status="2.h" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-9">
                        <desc>2.h</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2022-08-08T09:44:14.428Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.3" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-10">
                        <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2023-01-26T10:27:08.587Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.4" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-11">
                        <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#admin" when="2023-07-30T22:39:48.323Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.5" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-12">
                        <desc>TEI migrated to 2.19.0</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-07-01T14:09:28.352Z" type="translation-status" status="2.g" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-13">
                        <desc>2.g</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-07-01T14:09:28.352Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.6" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-14">
                        <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-07-01T14:10:16.351Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.7" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-22">
                        <desc>Auto (update-contributors)</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-20T14:51:56.191Z" type="translation-status" status="2.f" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-23">
                        <desc>2.f</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2024-08-20T14:51:56.191Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.8" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-24">
                        <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2025-01-13T10:40:46.165Z" type="translation-status" status="2.e" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-25">
                        <desc>2.e</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2025-01-13T10:40:46.165Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.9" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-26">
                        <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2025-01-24T12:57:06.085Z" type="translation-status" status="2.d" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-27">
                        <desc>2.d</desc>
                    </change>
                    <change who="#line-tofte" when="2025-01-24T12:57:06.085Z" type="text-version" status="0.0.10" xml:id="UT22084-001-005-28">
                        <desc>Auto (update-publication-status)</desc>
                    </change>
                </revisionDesc>
            </fileDesc>
        </teiHeader>
    <!-- Body reconstructed from the published 84000 EPUB (assets/epub/toh1-5.epub);
         the editorial master TEI is not publicly released, so per-node tid/xml:id and
         reading-room folio milestones are absent. Endnotes are inlined as <note place="end">. -->
    <text>
        <front>
            <div type="summary">
                <head type="summary">Summary</head>
            <p n="s.1"><hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> is the fifth chapter of<hi rend="italic"> The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi>, which has seventeen chapters in all. In the preceding three chapters of <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi>, the rules, rites, and procedures needed to establish and maintain a Buddhist monastic community are introduced. The present chapter opens with a narrative set in a border region beyond the Buddhist heartland. This story, which is also found in the <hi rend="italic">Divyāvadāna</hi>, depicts Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa delivering an epistle from his teacher Mahākātyāyana in south India to the Buddha in north India. In his message, the venerable Mahākātyāyana conveys five difficulties faced by monastic communities in far-flung places where local conditions and customs differ from those in the central Buddhist lands of Magadha, Kośala, and the Vṛji Republic. In response, the Buddha relaxes the rules for monks living in such places to allow that (1) ordination in border regions may be done by a group of five monks that includes a vinaya holder; (2) monks may bathe regularly; (3) sandals with a single lining may be kept and worn; (4) leather ground-spreads and ground-spread covers may be used; and (5) no one is at fault if the robes sent by a monk to another monk are lost on the way. This chapter is also the first of five chapters in <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi> that contain the Buddha’s detailed rulings on acceptable forms of material support‍—necessities of clothing, food, medicine, and shelter‍—allowed for monks. In this, <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>, the Buddha also relaxes rules governing the use of beds, seats, carriages, sandals, etc., to allow the use of some conveniences for the ill, the elderly, and those otherwise unable to manage.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="acknowledgment">
                <head type="acknowledgment">Acknowledgements</head>
            <p n="ac.1">This text was translated by Cuilan Liu, Jamyang Rinchen, Andy Francis, and Sue Roach. The introduction was written by Bob Miller and Sue Roach. Thanks to Shayne Clarke for commenting on a draft of the introduction.</p>
            <p n="ac.2">The translation was completed under the patronage and supervision of 84000: Translating the Words of the Buddha. Bob Miller edited the translation and the introduction, and Ven. Konchog Norbu copyedited the text. Martina Cotter was in charge of the digital publication process.</p>
            <p n="ac.3">The translation of this text has been made possible through the generous sponsorship of Xun Wang, Kebin Wang, Xiaojuan Dang, and Ziqing Xu.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="introduction">
                <head type="introduction">Introduction</head>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="section">Ordination and Allowances in Border Regions</head>
                <p n="i.1">In <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Cloth</hi>,<note place="end">For an overview of <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi> and its contents, see the introduction to <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Going Forth</hi>, i.9.</note> the Buddha explains that wearing hides is prohibited because doing so is “a badge of the non-Buddhist.”<note place="end">“Hide” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">g.yang gzhi</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">ajina</hi>). “Badge of the non-Buddhist” or, lit., “tīrthika standard” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">mu stegs pa’i rgyal mtshan</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">tīrthikadhvaja</hi>). See Toh 1-7, F.91.a: <hi rend="italic">btsun pa bdag g.yang gzhi ’chang bar ’tshal lo// bcom ldan ’das kyis bka’ stsal pa/ gti mug ’di ni mu stegs pa’i rgyal mtshan yin no zhes bya ba nas ’gal tshabs can du ’gyur ro zhes bya ba’i bar gong ma bzhin du’o</hi>.</note> Some non-Buddhist renunciants were known for wearing animal hides; it was, in a sense, their trademark.<note place="end">Olivelle (2018, p. 237) writes of forest hermits in the Brahmanical traditions (Skt. <hi rend="italic">vanaprastha</hi>), “The rejection of cultural mediation in every aspect of life defines the hermit’s asceticism. This is true not just of habitat and food, but in other areas such as clothes, which are made out of tree barks and animal skins.”</note> And therefore, so as not to be confused with them, Buddhist monks should not wear animal hides. This ruling in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Cloth</hi> suggests that monks’ robes were a type of uniform that marked the wearer and symbolically communicated their sectarian identity as Buddhist monks.</p>
                <p n="i.2">A different concern is in evidence in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>’s stories and rules, though: adapting monastic rules to ease life for monks living beyond the Buddhist heartland.<note place="end">The order of these two might suggest that Buddhist monks faced an increased need to “trademark” their look as they traveled and settled beyond the Buddhist heartland.</note> As the Buddhist saṅgha grew in the centuries before the Common Era, monks took up residence in different parts of India. Customs and material goods, along with the flora and the fauna, differed from those in the countries or “city-states”<note place="end">“Country” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">yul</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">janapada</hi>). For more on the countries or city-states of north India and Pakistan at the time of the Buddha, see Erdosy 1995, Erdosy 1988, and Allchin and Erdosy 1995.</note> of Magadha, Kośala, Kāśī, Vatsa, and the Vṛji Republic, where the Buddhist saṅgha first emerged and flourished. In such different circumstances, adhering to the monastic rules was not always practicable, prompting Buddhist monks living in these areas to seek special dispensations or allowances. The frame narrative of <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> is set in one of these diaspora communities in the frontier country of Aśmaka.<note place="end"><hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> situates its first narrative “in the frontier country of Aśmaka” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">rdo can zhes bya ba’i yul gyi mtha’ na</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">aśmāparāntakeṣu jana­padeṣu</hi>). Edgerton (<hi rend="italic">aparāntaka</hi>, p. 44, col. 2) writes that the Skt. <hi rend="italic">aparāntaka</hi> can refer (1) specifically to the country of Aparānta, or (2) more generally to the western border of Magadha. Rotman (2008, p. 392, n. 85) identifies Aśma/Aśmaka with Aśvaka (Pali Assaka) in present-day Maharashtra, which was one of the sixteen great countries (Skt. <hi rend="italic">mahājanapada</hi>) of ancient India. In the Pali version of Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s story, however, Soṇa Koṭikaṇṇa visits his mother at home in the village of Kuraraghara in Avanti, another of the <hi rend="italic">mahājanapada</hi>; see entry on “Soṇa-Kuṭikaṇṇa, Soṇa-Koṭikaṇṇa” in Malalasekera (1937, online 2021). Thus, Mūlasarvāstivādin and Theravādin sources both situate this story in the south, but in different <hi rend="italic">mahājanapada</hi>.</note></p>
                <p n="i.3">In Aśmaka, the venerable Mahākātyāyana reports, cattle trample the earth, leaving the ground rough and rocky, so the people sit on ground-spreads and ground-spread covers made from sheepskin, cowhide, deerskin, and goatskin, whereas in other places in India the people usually sit on seats made of wool, tree bark, cotton, or a cotton-wool mix. The venerable Mahākātyāyana is concerned because, when he and his students are invited into patrons’ homes and offered a seat, they are invariably offered a seat made of leather. And yet they are obliged to refuse, since the Buddha had not allowed it. Since the venerable Mahākātyāyana does not cite a specific prohibition, we are left to speculate as to the exact reasons for his misgivings. In the context of the frame story, when the Buddha allows monks in border regions to sit on leather seats, bathe daily, and wear sandals with one lining all in one fell swoop, he seems to adopt a pragmatic stance in allowing these conveniences, which do not grossly transgress Buddhist principles of nonharming and compassion.<note place="end">The theme of compassion appears again in the story under the heading “Calf,” where the venerable Upananda, in a fit of pique, has a young calf killed for its hide. The theme of compassion is also found in the Buddha’s allowances at the behest of the venerable Pilindavatsa, who is chronically ill, under the heading “Carriage.” Here, as elsewhere in the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya, the Buddha relaxes rules for monks who are ill, elderly, or otherwise unable to manage. Another reason for relaxing restrictions emerges in the stories under the headings “Allow to Protect” and “Buskins,” where the Buddha relaxes restrictions so that fancy sandals and bearskins donated by patrons may be accepted, the first for personal use, the second for display in the monastery temple.</note></p>
                <p n="i.4">The most significant new adaptation adopted at Mahākātyāyana’s behest was the relaxation of rules for ordaining monks in border regions, which is why this initial story is summarized under the heading “Ordination by Five” in the chapter’s first summary. For the present-day ordination rite prescribed by the Buddha, a quorum of ten monks is needed. Here, the Buddha allows that a quorum of five monks (in which the fifth is a vinaya holder) will suffice to ordain monks in border regions like Aśmaka.<note place="end">See <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Going Forth</hi>, 1.471–1.473.</note> This consequential amendment to the community’s primary gatekeeping institution made it much easier to ordain new monks in the outlying kingdoms and city-states in which Buddhist monks increasingly found themselves in the centuries before and after the start of the Common Era.</p>
                <p n="i.5">Allowing ordination by five in border regions necessitated an official demarcation of center and periphery, so that monks would know where exactly a quorum of five would suffice for ordaining a new member. In <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>, the Buddha establishes the borders of the Buddhist heartland or “Center”<note place="end">This “Center” corresponds roughly with what Johannes Bronkhorst has called the cultural region of “Greater Magadha.” Bronkhorst has devoted several publications to distinguishing the religio-cultural regions of Greater Magadha, where Buddhists, Jains, Ājīvikas, and other groups first flourished, and the more westerly Kuru-Pañcāla region, where Brahmanical heirs to the Vedic tradition formed the dominant religious group. See esp. Bronkhorst 2011.</note> as extending, in modern geopolitical terms, as far east as Bengal, as far south as the Deccan, as far west as Delhi and Thanesar, and as far north as Uttarakhand.<note place="end">See Rotman 2008, p. 400, nn. 192, 195, and 196 for a more precise identification of the borders.</note> Beyond lay the frontier regions, where Buddhist monks lived, initially at least, only in small numbers.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="section">Negotiating the Middle Way</head>
                <p n="i.6">The remaining stories in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> fall into two types: (1) those in which Upananda alone or all members of the group of six take an allowance to such ostentatious lengths that the Buddha is forced to restrict it, and (2) those that feature other, mostly nameless and blameless monks whose struggles to cope with the ascetic life prompt the Buddha to relax the rules and allow conveniences. In stories of the second type, hardships posed by the physical environment, rather than wayward monks, prompt new allowances from the Buddha, such as when monks stub their toes and scrape their heels climbing Vulture Peak Mountain and the Buddha allows toe and heel covers.</p>
                <p n="i.7">In a recent article, Schopen succinctly identifies the two kinds of protagonist one tends to see in the canonical vinayas: “Most of the monks that cause trouble in vinaya texts are either nameless or members of the Group-of-Six.”<note place="end">Schopen 2022, p. 313.</note> Regarding Upananda and his band, Schopen notes that “each member of the Group [of Six] appears to be a literary creation meant to embody or stand for one or another common monastic failing or fault.”<note place="end">Schopen 2022, p. 313.</note> Upananda, for instance, personifies greed, as evidenced by the size of his estate at death. He appears so frequently in the canonical vinayas, Schopen observes, that he “may be one of the most fully developed characters in all of Indian literature.”<note place="end">Schopen 2022, p. 314. The nun Sthūlanandā plays a similar role in the portions of the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya addressed explicitly to nuns, nun probationers, and female novices.</note> In one of his more famous pieces, “The Learned Monk as a Comic Figure,” Schopen discusses passages that satirize Upananda and the group of six as greedy gluttons.<note place="end">See Schopen 2014, pp. 404–31.</note> The humor with which their transgressive antics are depicted evinces, Schopen argues, a familiarity with Indian drama on the part of the compilers of the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya.<note place="end">Schopen 2014, p. 418.</note></p>
                <p n="i.8">Here, in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>, Upananda and the group of six’s indulgent tendencies are sometimes juxtaposed against the restraint shown by monks committed to the “practices of the austere.”<note place="end">“Practice of austerity”: Tib. <hi rend="italic">sbyangs pa’i yon tan</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">dhūtaguṇa</hi>. On which, see Roach 2020.</note> Monks who engage in these practices live with only the barest of supports.<note place="end">Acceptable forms of “support” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">gnas</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">niśraya</hi>) are introduced during the ordination ceremony; see 1.591–1.601 of <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Going Forth</hi>.</note> Though austere, these practices are nevertheless sanctioned by the Buddha and thus demarcate the outer boundary of accepted Buddhist ascetic practice.</p>
                <p n="i.9">Narratively, then, the members of the group of six and their ascetic, forest-dwelling counterparts function as tropes in these stories, employed by the compilers as personifications of indulgence on the one hand and strict but acceptable asceticism on the other. The Bodhisattva, in his pursuit of awakening, famously rejected the more extreme forms of asceticism practiced by his contemporaries. In the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya, this turning point is retold in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Schisms in the Saṅgha</hi>, the seventeenth and final chapter of this text. There, the Buddha-to-be sits in a charnel ground, poked and prodded by children from the village who cannot tell whether he is dead or alive. Reflecting on the hardships he has endured and the fruits they bore, he concludes that the mortifying disciplines he has learned are not conducive to awakening. He wonders what kind of practice might suffice when suddenly he remembers a childhood experience of ease, felt while seated underneath a rose-apple tree in his father’s fields:</p>
                <q rend="block" n="i.10">“When I was living in the house of my father, the Śākyan Śuddhodana, I followed him to the fields he tilled and sat down in the shade of a rose-apple tree. There, free of desire, wrongdoing, and nonvirtue, I remember attaining the first dhyāna, which is endowed with thought, reflection, and the pleasure and ease born of solitude. <hi rend="italic">That</hi> is the path. <hi rend="italic">That</hi> is the practice. It enables knowledge, enables seeing, and enables unsurpassed, complete awakening, but it will not be easy for me, who has grown emaciated and weak, to cultivate that. I should inhale at ease and exhale at ease; I should take coarse porridge and gruel as food, massage my body with ghee and sesame oil, and bathe in soft water.”<note place="end">See Toh 1-17, vol. nga, folios 19.a–26.a, esp. 25.a–b. <hi rend="italic">de ’di snyam du dgongs te/ shes par nus pa dang / mthong bar nus pa dang / bla na med pa yang dag par rdzogs par byang chub par nus pa’i lam de gang yin snyam na/ de ’di snyam du dgongs te/ bdag yab shAkya zas gtsang gi khyim na gnas pa’i tshe zhing las kyi mtha’i drung du song nas shing ’dzam bu’i grib ma la ’dug ste/ ’dod pa las dben pa/ sdig pa mi dge ba’i chos las dben pa/ rtog pa dang bcas shing dpyod pa dang bcas pa/ dben pa las skyes pa’i dga’ ba dang / bde ba can bsam gtan dang po nye bar bsgrubs te gnas pa de mngon par dran te/ de ni lam yin/ de ni sgrub pa yin/ shes par nus pa yin/ mthong bar nus pa yin/ bla na med pa yang dag par rdzogs par byang chub par nus pa yin na/ de bdag gis bskyed du yang ’di ltar rid cing nyam chung la zhan pas sla ba ma yin te/ ma la bdag gis ci bder dbugs rngub pa dang / ci bder dbugs ’byung ba dang / ci bder ’bras chan dang zan dron gyi kha zas rags pa bza’ zhing lus mar sar dang til mar gyis byugs la chu ’jam pos lus bkru bar bya’o snyam ste/ de ci bder dbugs rngub pa dang / ci bder dbugs ’byung ba dang / ci bder ’bras chan dang zan dron gyi zhal zas rags pa gsol zhing sku til mar dang mar sar gyis byugs nas chu ’jam pos sku ’khru bar mdzad do</hi>.</note></q>
                <p n="i.11">Of course, Buddhist monks were not to take such accounts as license to do as they pleased. Again and again, in the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya in general and this chapter in particular, those who freely indulge their whims and pleasures are censured by brahmins and prominent householders and accused of being “obsessed with sense pleasures.” Inevitably, these accusations prompt new rules, with which the monastic “middle way” between indulgence and self-mortification is further defined.<note place="end">The asceticism promoted in the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya can be described as a soft, permissive, and sometimes simply rhetorical asceticism, at least in comparison to the depiction of more severe, self-mortifying trends esteemed by non-Buddhist <hi rend="italic">śramaṇa</hi> or “ascetic” groups of the Buddha’s time. Freiberger (2006) links this “moderate” asceticism to the “Middle Way” between indulgence and self-mortification.</note> Stories featuring Upananda and the rest of the group of six can be found under the headings “Wide Beds,” “Carriage,” “Swimming,” “Cow’s Tail,” “Inappropriate Motifs,” “Allow to Protect,” and “Lace Up Crosswise.”</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="section">Vinaya Rulemaking</head>
                <p n="i.12">The sequence of stories and rulings in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> well demonstrates how the Vinaya is “reactive” in its rulemaking.<note place="end">Clarke (2021, p. 15) has used the phrase “reactive” to describe the Vinaya’s approach to rules. Clarke reports that this is similar to what has been described in Chinese and Japanese scholarship as “legislation follows transgression” (Ch. <hi rend="italic">suifan suishi</hi>; Jpn. <hi rend="italic">zuibon zuisei</hi>, <hi rend="italic">隨犯隨制</hi>). The extant Buddhist vinayas all employ this type of “legal casuistry,” to borrow a categorization used by Garfield (2021, p. 58). For a survey of all the extant vinayas, see Clarke 2015.</note> Rules are modified in response to different circumstances, either relaxed on compassionately pragmatic grounds or restricted to rein in indulgence. For example:</p>
                <list type="unordered">
                    <item>The Buddha prohibits high and wide seats, then allows monks to sit on them, but only in the home of a householder.</item>
                    <item>The Buddha prohibits monks from traveling by carriage, then allows the ill and elderly to do so.</item>
                    <item>Monks may not swim, but they may learn how.</item>
                    <item>Monks may not touch women, but they may rescue a woman who is drowning in a river.</item>
                    <item>Monks may not use leather items, but they may hold on to an animal’s tail when crossing a river, and they may keep an animal bladder as a floatation aid for crossing rivers.</item>
                    <item>Monks may not wear wooden sandals, except inside a householder’s home at the householder’s request. If laypeople offer wooden sandals, they should be accepted.</item>
                    <item>The Buddha allows monks to wear rope sandals after monks develop sores from sandals made of bamboo leaves and muñja grass.</item>
                    <item>The Buddha prohibits sandals with multiple linings but then allows them when donated by a householder who has already used them.</item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="section">The Story of Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa</head>
                <p n="i.13"><hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> features stories with two monks named Śroṇa. The second of these, Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa, is the main protagonist of a short but fascinating narrative included in the second summary. Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa, known as Soṇa-Koḷiviśa Thera in the Pali Vinaya, was the son of a wealthy merchant from Campā. His privileged background is apparent on the soles of his feet, from which grow long golden hairs as a result of being carried everywhere. The group of six taunt him for being so coddled and express doubt about whether he will be able to exert the effort needed to progress in the Buddha’s teaching. Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa, hearing their taunts, refuses to be discouraged and seeks out Ānanda, asking how a determined person might remain in absorption on the teaching. When Ānanda tells him it is through walking, Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa practices walking meditation with such zeal that his feet bleed.<note place="end">Malalasekera reports that Soṇa-Koḷiviśa Thera won eminence among the Buddha’s close disciples as “foremost of those who strove energetically” (Pali: <hi rend="italic">aggaṃ āraddhaviriyānaṃ</hi>). See Malalasekera 2021, “Soṇa-Koḷiviśa Thera.”</note> The Buddha, having compassion for him, allows Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa to put a lining in his sandals to protect his feet. But Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa refuses the preferential treatment and agrees to wear sandals with one lining only if all monks are allowed to do so, a condition the Buddha then grants.</p>
                <p n="i.14">The second Śroṇa is Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, whose <hi rend="italic">avadāna</hi><hi rend="italic"></hi> provides the frame story for Mahākātyāyana and his five-point epistle to the Buddha, discussed above. Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s avadāna is the second of several avadānas extracted from <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi> for the <hi rend="italic">Divyāvadāna</hi> collection.<note place="end">Though Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s avadāna is related first in the <hi rend="italic">Divyāvadāna</hi> itself, Saṅgharakṣita’s avadāna comes before, in the first chapter of <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi>; see the story under the heading “Creatures” (4.113–4.329) in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Going Forth</hi>. This avadāna has been translated into English twice recently from the Sanskrit in publications that include the whole <hi rend="italic">Divyāvadāna</hi>. See the introductions to both volumes for an overview of this collection of avadānas. For the translation of Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s avadāna specifically, see Tatelman (2005, pp. 25–101), who provides a Sanskrit edition on the facing page of the translation, and Rotman (2008, pp. 39–70), who gives an annotated translation.</note> The Sanskrit word <hi rend="italic">avadāna</hi><hi rend="italic"></hi> refers to one of nine or twelve genres used to classify the Buddha’s early teachings.<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">rtogs brjod</hi>. On the ninefold and twelvefold classifications of the Buddha’s words, see Lamotte (1988, pp. 143–49), Hirakawa (1990, pp. 74–75), and Anālayo (2016).</note> In the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya, avadānas narrate the “karmic history” of their subjects’ accomplishments, both on the Buddhist path and in the world. The subject of an avadāna is typically one of the Buddha’s close disciples or a notable lay follower. Furthermore, according to Andy Rotman, avadānas follow a tripartite structure that consists of:<note place="end">We have added numbers in parentheses, italics, and bold type for emphasis. Rotman 2008, p. 5.</note> (1) a story in the present tense in which characters discover the benefits of Buddhist practice and meet the Buddha; (2) a story of the past detailing the deeds done by those characters in a previous lifetime that have now come to karmic fruition; and (3) a juncture at which time the Buddha‍—who is quite literally an “omniscient narrator”‍—identifies the characters in the story of the past with those in the story of the present.</p>
                <p n="i.15">The story of Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa here follows that threefold structure. The narrative begins in the “present” (i.e., the Buddha’s time) in the village of Vāsava in the frontier country of Aśmaka, in south India, where Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa grows up in luxury.<note place="end">The <hi rend="italic">Cammakkhandaka</hi>, the Pali parallel to the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">Carmavastu</hi> or <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>, gives Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s name as Soṇakuṭikaṇṇa and places him in the <hi rend="italic">mahājanapada</hi> of Avanti; see the <hi rend="italic">Cammakkhandaka</hi>’s “Soṇakuṭikaṇṇavatthu.”</note> Before he squanders his family fortune, his father sends him out as a caravan leader to the Isle of Jewels to collect the island’s titular bounty. But, on their return to India, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa is separated from his companions and stumbles upon a city of hungry ghosts. Unable to resist the urge to enter, he wanders the city for twelve years, encountering various hungry ghosts,<note place="end">For a discussion of the type of being known as a hungry ghost, see Rotman 2021. Plate 1 shows Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa encountering the hungry ghosts in the iron city.</note> from whom he learns of a great Buddhist monk named Mahākātyāyana.</p>
                <p n="i.16">On his return to the country of Aśmaka, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa seeks out the venerable Mahākātyāyana and requests permission to go forth, and be ordained as a monk. But the venerable Mahākātyāyana urges him to deliver the messages he received from the hungry ghosts first. Once he has done so, the venerable Mahākātyāyana allows Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa to go forth. But he must wait to be ordained as a monk until Mahākātyāyana can gather the necessary ten monks, which is difficult given the paucity of monks in that border region of south India. Mahākātyāyana’s students spend the three months of rains scattered about in different places, practicing yoga (i.e., meditation) and receiving instruction. After the rains, Mahākātyāyana’s many students come to see their teacher to resolve their outstanding questions. Through this process, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa attains arhatship and is ordained as a monk by Mahākātyāyana and a gathering of ten.</p>
                <p n="i.17">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa then seeks permission to see and serve the Buddha in person, which Mahākātyāyana grants. It is then that the venerable Mahākātyāyana charges Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa with delivering his epistle to the Buddha, informing the Blessed One of five issues that monks face in the south of India. In response to these concerns, the Buddha allows that (1) ordination in border regions may be done by a group of five monks that includes a vinaya holder; (2) monks may bathe regularly; (3) sandals with a single lining may be kept and worn; (4) leather ground-spreads and ground-spread covers may be kept; and (5) no one is at fault if the robes sent by a monk to another monk are lost on the way.</p>
                <p n="i.18">The Buddha then narrates a story of the past about a merchant who took care of a stūpa dedicated to the Buddha Kāśyapa and made the aspiration to be reborn into a rich family and attain the Dharma. Finally, the “juncture,” or narrative denouement, is reached with the Buddha’s identification of the merchant with Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa.</p>
                <p n="i.19">Embedded in Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s story are a series of shorter avadānas or “karmic histories” revealing what each of the hungry ghosts did in his or her former life that led to their rebirth in one of the lower realms of existence. The repetition found in these stories serves to reinforce the underlying principle of karmic cause and effect, which the Buddha sums up at the end of Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s avadāna:</p>
                <q rend="block" n="i.20">“The ripened fruits of wholly negative actions are wholly negative, while the ripened fruits of wholly positive actions are wholly positive, and the ripened fruits of of mixed actions are mixed. Monks, therefore abandon wholly negative and mixed actions, and seek wholly positive actions. Monks, this is how you should train.”</q>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
                <head type="section">Textual Editions</head>
                <p n="i.21">The Mūlasarvāstivādin <hi rend="italic">Chapter on Leather</hi> has survived in at least three languages:<note place="end">See Clarke 2015, pp. 73–81, for an overview of the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya and the languages in which it has been at least partially transmitted, including, e.g., Mongolian.</note> Sanskrit, Chinese, and Tibetan. The Sanskrit original was discovered in Gilgit (in present-day northern Kashmir) in the 1930s.<note place="end">See Clarke 2014 for an introduction to the Gilgit manuscripts in general and the Vinaya texts among them in particular. See Clarke (2014, p. 21) for a bibliographical survey of the present chapter.</note> The Sanskrit manuscript is fragmentary, with approximately 20 percent of the text missing. The manuscript itself dates to around the sixth to the seventh century, which is probably two to three centuries after the redaction of the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya closed around the fourth or fifth century.<note place="end">Schopen (2006, pp. 316–17) and Olivelle (2007, p. 177) both argue that the canonical vinayas took shape between the Mauryan and Gupta empires, circa 300 <hi rend="small-caps">ʙᴄᴇ</hi>–400 <hi rend="small-caps">ᴄᴇ</hi>. These are approximate and tentative dates. Furthermore, it is unclear when in that process the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya was written down. However, writing on the Indian subcontinent began as early as the third c. <hi rend="small-caps">ʙᴄᴇ</hi> under the Mauryas and later continued in the Deccan under Sātavāhana rule and in the northwestern lands ruled by the Kuṣāṇa empire. See Strauch (2022, pp. 10–19), who compares manuscript evidence with regard to geographical and chronological distribution and concludes that changes over time and space call into question notions of a fixed “canonical language” within any Buddhist tradition.</note> These manuscripts are available in a textual edition published by Nalinaksha Dutt.<note place="end">Dutt, N. (1942–50), <hi rend="italic">Gilgit Buddhist Manuscripts. Vol. III</hi>. The Sanskrit for this chapter is in Vol. III, pt. 4 (1950), pp. 159–210. The Sanskrit is also available online in a GRETIL edition.</note> Facsimiles of the manuscripts are included in <hi rend="italic">Vinaya Texts</hi>, edited by Shayne Clarke, along with an excellent introduction, bibliography, and textual concordance.<note place="end">Clarke 2015. The eleven <hi rend="italic">Carmavastu</hi> folios are described on p. 21, and the photographs are in plates 32–46.</note></p>
                <p n="i.22">The present translation of <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> is based on the Tibetan translation in the Degé Kangyur, with reference to the Stok Palace recension where Degé is unclear. The Tibetan translation of a Sanskrit Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya was made around the first decade of the ninth century. It is assumed to be complete, with some caveats.<note place="end">See Clarke 2016–17, p. 201, n. 1.</note></p>
                <p n="i.23">We have also consulted the Chinese translation carried out by Yijing (635–713 <hi rend="small-caps">ᴄᴇ</hi>). Yijing brought back hundreds of texts to China from India and Southeast Asia in the last decades of the seventh century, including a Sanskrit Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya. Yijing translated seven chapters of <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi> from that into Chinese, including <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>.<note place="end">See Yijing’s Chinese translation of <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> (Taishō 1447: 1048c1–1057b19). In addition, portions of the <hi rend="italic">Sarvāstivāda­vinaya</hi> (Taishō 1435: 178a14–184b17), <hi rend="italic">Mahīśāsaka­vinaya</hi> (Taishō 1421: 144a12–147a25), and <hi rend="italic">Dharma­guptaka­vinaya</hi> (Taishō 1428: 843b11–849b9) were consulted.</note></p>
                <p n="i.24">A parallel to the Mūlasarvāstivādin <hi rend="italic">Chapter on Leather</hi> is found in the <hi rend="italic">Cammakkhandaka</hi> of the Pali Vinaya of the Theravādins.<note place="end">See Horner’s translation.</note> In the Pali language account, the order of the two Śroṇas is reversed. The Pali version opens with the story of Śroṇa (Soṇa Koḷivisa) and his bleeding feet, with a much-abbreviated account of Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s questions occurring toward the end of the chapter.<note place="end">For details of the two Soṇas in the Pali texts, see entries on “Soṇa-Kuṭikaṇṇa, Soṇa-Koṭikaṇṇa” and “Soṇa Koḷivisa Thera” in Malalasekera’s <hi rend="italic">Dictionary of Pali Proper Names</hi> (2021).</note> For an overview of monastic footwear from India to China, see Ann Heirman’s article (2016) <hi rend="italic">Shoes in Buddhist Monasteries from India to China: From Practical Attire to Symbol</hi>.</p>
            </div>
            </div>
        </front>
        <body>
            <div type="translation">
                <head type="translation">The Translation</head>
                <head type="titleHon">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</head>
                <head type="titleMain">The Chapter on Leather</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Summary 1</head>
                    <p n="1.1">A summary of <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>:<note place="end">Translating the Tib. <hi rend="italic">khrus</hi> here as “swimming” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">chu bo la rgyu ba spyod</hi>) based on the narrative and ruling found under that section. The full summary here is not extant in Sanskrit.</note><note place="end"><hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> does not have a single global summary (Tib. <hi rend="italic">spyi sdom</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">piṇḍoddāna</hi>) like the preceding chapters in <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi>. Instead, there are three summaries (Tib. <hi rend="italic">sdom</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">uddāna</hi>). The material covered in this first summary takes up approximately two-thirds of the text. The second summary is found on F.272.b while the third is on F.276.a. The chapter ends at 1.333.</note><note place="end">As there is no separate narrative setting after the section on carriages, we have grouped the items from “carriages” to “wooden sandals” in the summary together in one heading.</note> </p>
                    <lg n="1.1">
                        <l>Ordination by five; Wide beds; calf; and Carriage, swimming, cow’s tail, Wooden sandals, and inappropriate motifs.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <div type="chapter">
                        <head type="chapter">Ordination by Five</head>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s Birth and Upbringing</head>
                            <p n="1.2">The Blessed Buddha was staying in Prince Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park.<note place="end">The Tibetan text does not mention “near Śrāvastī” as is usual in this <hi rend="italic">nidāna</hi> or “setting” formula.</note> At that time, in a village called Vāsava in the frontier country of Aśmaka, there was a householder named Balasena who was rich, wealthy, and prosperous, with vast and extensive holdings, who possessed the wealth of Vaiśravaṇa,<note place="end">One of the Four Great Kings (<hi rend="italic">mahārāja</hi>), demigods who were converted by the Buddha and served as guardians of the world. Vaiśravaṇa was the guardian of the north and was fabled for his wealth. See BHSD, p. 425.</note> whose wealth rivaled that of Vaiśravaṇa. Having taken a wife of equal caste, he frolicked, took pleasure, and made love with her. But although he frolicked, took pleasure, and made love with her, they produced neither son nor daughter. With his hand pressed to his cheek, he lamented, “I have accumulated all this wealth for the household, and yet I have neither son nor daughter. And so, since I have no heir, all of my possessions will be appropriated by the king upon my death.” He sat there, brooding.</p>
                            <p n="1.3">His loved ones, relatives, and friends asked, “Why are you brooding? Pray to the gods! Then you will have a son.”</p>
                            <p n="1.4">Having considered it, he thought, “They’re right. Very well then, I’ll pray to the gods for a son.” So, childless and out of deep longing for a son, he prayed to gods such as Śiva, Varuṇa, Kubera, Śakra, and Brahmā, and then supplicated the god of the park, the god of the forest, the god of the crossroads, the god at the junction of three roads, the god who accepts oblations, as well as his hereditary god, who shared his Dharma and was always connected to him.</p>
                            <p n="1.5">It is popularly said that sons and daughters are born as the result of such prayers. But this is not the case. If it were the case, then it would be so for everyone, and, for example, everyone would have a thousand sons like a universal monarch. Instead, when three conditions are present, sons and daughters are born. What three conditions? The father and mother, feeling passion, have intercourse; the mother is healthy and ovulating; and a gandharva is nearby.<note place="end">Here, “gandharva” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">dri za</hi>) refers to a being in the intermediate state. Such beings linger in this state until they are drawn, in the case of one who will be reborn as a human, to a couple copulating. Driven by lust, they are said to enter or “become conjoined with” the male’s sperm and the female’s ovum. Thus, while the sperm and ovum serve as the direct or substantial cause for the gandharva’s new body, the gandharva’s mind acts as the direct cause for the new being’s stream of consciousness.</note> When these three conditions are present, sons and daughters are born.</p>
                            <p n="1.6">As Balasena sat making such earnest entreaties, a being in its last existence who was seeking a host, who had grasped the essence of liberation, who had turned toward nirvāṇa, who had turned away from saṃsāra, who did not seek birth and death in any kind of conditioned existence, and who was taking its last body, died in the realm of the gods and entered the womb of Balasena’s wife.</p>
                            <p n="1.7">Some women wise in nature possess five distinctive characteristics. What are the five? She knows when a man is in the grip of desire and she knows when his desire has abated; she knows when the time is right and knows her menstrual cycle; she knows when a being has entered her womb; she knows where the being in her womb has come from; and she knows if it is a boy and knows if it is a girl. If it will be a boy, it settles and rests on the right side of the belly. If it is a girl, it settles and rests on the left side of the belly.</p>
                            <p n="1.8">Glad and delighted, she said to her husband, “Son of a noble one, take joy in our fortune! For I am pregnant, and since the child has settled and is resting on the right side of my belly, there is no doubt that it will be a boy.”</p>
                            <p n="1.9">Glad and delighted too, he was inspired to speak these inspired words:<note place="end">Skt. <hi rend="italic">udānam udānayati</hi>.</note> “May I see the face of the son I have long wished for! May he be in harmony with me and not in conflict with me! May he carry out my duties! May he, having been supported by me, support me in return! May he enjoy his inheritance! May he secure the family line for a long time! When we are dead and the time is right, may he offer donations, whether few or many. When he has made merit, may he assign the reward in our names, saying, ‘Wherever those two have been reborn, may this go there and follow them!’ ”</p>
                            <p n="1.10">Upon learning that a being had entered his wife’s womb, Balasena installed her in the upper story of their mansion and, to ensure that the being in her womb would reach full term, he provided her with what was needed for the cold when it was cold and what was needed for the heat when it was hot. On the doctor’s advice, her food was not to be too bitter, too sour, too salty, too sweet, too spicy, or too astringent; and so she was given food that was devoid of bitterness, sourness, sweetness, spiciness, and astringency. With her body adorned with necklaces and strings of pearls, she was moved from bed to bed, from seat to seat, without touching the floor, like an apsarā floating through a pleasure grove, with Balasena seeing that she did not even hear the slightest of unpleasant sounds.</p>
                            <p n="1.11">After eight or nine months had passed, she gave birth to a boy who was well formed, pleasing to the eye, handsome, with a golden complexion, a parasol-shaped head, long arms, a large and broad brow, eyebrows that met in the middle, a high-bridged nose, and a jewel-encrusted earring in one ear.</p>
                            <p n="1.12">The householder Balasena summoned each and every appraiser of jewels who lived in the village of Vāsava to examine the jewel and said to them, “Gentlemen, determine the value of this jewel.” </p>
                            <p n="1.12">They said, “We cannot determine the value of this jewel.”</p>
                            <p n="1.13">Customarily, when the value of a jewel cannot be determined, it is valued at ten million. So they said, “Householder, this jewel is worth ten million.”</p>
                            <p n="1.14">His relatives gathered, and for three weeks‍—twenty-one days‍—they held a great celebratory feast for the newborn to name him. </p>
                            <p n="1.14">“Gentlemen, what name should we give the boy?”</p>
                            <p n="1.15">His friends replied, “Since he was born under the constellation of Śravaṇa, and with an earring embellished with a jewel worth ten million in one ear, the boy’s name should be Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa (Born Under Śravaṇa with an Ear Worth Ten Million).” So he was named Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa.</p>
                            <p n="1.16">On the very day that Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa was born, two sons were born to servants of the householder Balasena. They named one Dāsaka (Servant) and named the other Pālaka (Protector).</p>
                            <p n="1.17">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa was entrusted to eight nurses‍—two nurses to cuddle him, two nurses to breastfeed him, two nurses to clean him, and two nurses to play with him as companions. Nourished and fortified by the best of the best milk, yogurt, fresh butter, clarified butter, cream, and other special provisions given to him by these eight nurses, he grew quickly like a lotus in a lake.</p>
                            <p n="1.18">When he grew up, he was entrusted to tutors in letters<note place="end">To “write” (Skt. <hi rend="italic">lipi</hi>; Tib. <hi rend="italic">yi ge</hi>).</note> and numbers;<note place="end">“Numbers” (Skt. <hi rend="italic">saṃkhyā</hi>; Tib. <hi rend="italic">rtsis</hi>). In commenting on this same word in the same formulaic passage earlier in <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi>, Kalyāṇamitra explains that this to refers to learning to calculate using number names (i.e., tens, hundreds, thousands, etc.); see Toh 4113, F.184.b: <hi rend="italic">rtsis zhes bya ba ni tshig gis brtsi ba ste rtsis su bya ba’o</hi>.</note> in how to calculate and how to reckon by hand; in yields, deposits, entrustments, and withdrawals;<note place="end">According to Kalyāṇamitra, a “yield” (Skt. <hi rend="italic">uddhāra</hi>; Tib. <hi rend="italic">dbyung ba</hi>) refers to “a yield of material such as bamboo and so forth.” A “deposit” (Skt. <hi rend="italic">nyāsa</hi>; Tib. <hi rend="italic">gzhug pa</hi>) is when that is stored internally, while an “entrustment” (Skt. <hi rend="italic">nikṣepa</hi>: Tib. <hi rend="italic">gzhag pa</hi>) is when that is placed externally. See Toh 4113, F.184.b: <hi rend="italic">’byung ba zhes bya ba ni sprog ma la sogs pa nas rdzas ’byung ba’o //gzhug pa zhes bya ba ni de nyid kyi nang du gzhag pa’o//gzhag pa zhes bya ba ni phyi rol du gzhag pa’o</hi>. Kalyāṇamitra does not gloss “withdrawals” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">len pa</hi>, Skt. *<hi rend="italic">udgraha</hi>?).</note> and in the appraisal of land, the appraisal of cloth, the appraisal of jewels, the appraisal of elephants, the appraisal of horses, the appraisal of women, the appraisal of men, and the appraisal of wood. He perfected and discerned those eight appraisals and became expert in reading.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa the Caravan Leader</head>
                            <p n="1.19">His father built for him three residences‍—one each for winter, spring, and summer. And, after also having three pleasure gardens constructed‍—one each for winter, spring, and summer‍—Balasena arranged three wives for Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa: an elder, middle, and junior. There, on the upper stories of his mansions, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa frolicked, took pleasure, and made love with his wives, to the accompaniment of music played by female musicians.</p>
                            <p n="1.20">Meanwhile, the householder Balasena was always working hard at his farming. Seeing his father always working hard at his farming, Śroṇa asked him, “Father, why are you always working hard at your farming?”</p>
                            <p n="1.21">“Son,” he replied, “if I frolicked, took pleasure, and made love on the upper story of the mansion, to the accompaniment of music played by female musicians, as you do, before long our wealth would dwindle, and then be exhausted and spent.” </p>
                            <p n="1.21">“If that is the case, Father, I shall take some goods and go abroad,” he replied.</p>
                            <p n="1.22">“Son, I have such jewels that even if you were to use them as you do sesame seeds, rice, jujube berries, or peas, the jewels I possess would not be exhausted.” </p>
                            <p n="1.22">“Father, I shall take some goods and go abroad,” he said again and again.</p>
                            <p n="1.23">Realizing that his son was determined, the householder Balasena granted his permission.</p>
                            <p n="1.24">Balasena announced to the village of Vāsava, “Merchant gentlemen residing in the village of Vāsava, listen! Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa will take to the great sea, so whoever among you gentlemen would like to take to the great sea together with Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa‍—with a pilot, free of tariff, with no need for fare, with no need for tolls<note place="end">“Fare” (Skt. <hi rend="italic">ātarpaṇi</hi>; Tib. <hi rend="italic">bsel ba’i rngan pa</hi>). Here, “no need for tolls” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">’gru btsas mi dgos pa</hi>) is missing in the Skt.</note>‍—pack your merchandise for a voyage on the great sea.” Five hundred merchants then readied their merchandise for the voyage on the great sea.</p>
                            <p n="1.25">The householder Balasena invited the five hundred merchants to a feast in his own home and, having offered them a meal, said, “Listen, merchant gentlemen! As Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa is my son, he is yours, too. So may you dispel dangers and furnish assistance to him.”</p>
                            <p n="1.26">“Master, we will do as you say,” the merchants said, heeding the householder Balasena.</p>
                            <p n="1.27">The householder Balasena then said to Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, “Son, just as you would listen to and carry out what I say, you should listen to and carry out what these five hundred merchants say.”</p>
                            <p n="1.28">The householder Balasena reflected, “On what sort of mount should I send Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa?” He thought, “If one rides on an elephant while traveling, an elephant can be hard to maintain and hard to support.<note place="end">The Tibetan of <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> gives <hi rend="italic">bskyang ba</hi> or “maintain.” The Sanskrit of <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> here reads <hi rend="italic">sukumārā</hi> or “gentle” where the <hi rend="italic">Divyāvadāna</hi> reads <hi rend="italic">sudūrakṣyā</hi>, which Tatelman (2005, p. 37) translates as “very difficult to guard” and Rotman renders “nice to sit on” (2008, p. 43).</note> A horse is also hard to maintain and hard to support. Since a donkey is easy to feed and has a good memory, I will send him on a donkey.”</p>
                            <p n="1.29">He then said to him, “Son, do not travel at the front or at the rear of the party. If a bandit is strong, he will attack the front of the caravan. If he is weak, he will attack the rear of the caravan. So you should travel in the middle of the merchants, for it is said that if the caravan leader is lost, the caravan will be lost.”</p>
                            <p n="1.30">To Dāsaka and Pālaka he said, “On no account whatsoever should the two of you leave Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa behind!”</p>
                            <p n="1.31">Later on, after performing the rituals for an auspicious, fortunate, and successful journey, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa went to his mother and said, “Mother, I’ve come to pay my respects, for I am setting off for the great sea.”<note place="end">The Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">Chapter on Leather</hi> has <hi rend="italic">mahā­samudram avatarāmi</hi>, or “setting off for the great sea,” where the Tibetan reads simply “leaving.”</note></p>
                            <p n="1.32">She began to cry, and he asked, “Why are you weeping, Mother?” </p>
                            <p n="1.32">His mother continued crying as she said, “Son, I wonder<note place="end">Following Stok Palace <hi rend="italic">snyam mo</hi>, which makes better sense than Degé <hi rend="italic">snyam mod</hi>.</note> whether I will ever see you again alive!”</p>
                            <p n="1.33">He reflected, “I have performed the ritual for good fortune, but now she speaks so inauspiciously just as I’m leaving.”<note place="end">Like the <hi rend="italic">Divyāvadāna</hi>, the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">Chapter on Leather</hi> depicts Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa as saying, “Mother, I set off for the great sea having performed the rituals for an auspicious, fortunate, and successful journey, yet you speak so inauspiciously.” See: <hi rend="italic">amba ahaṃ kṛtakautuka­maṅgala­svastyayano mahāsamudraṃ saṃprasthitaḥ / tvaṃ cedṛśāny amaṅgalāni karoṣi</hi>.</note> Irritated, he said, “Can you not see the miserable realms?”<note place="end">Translation following the rendering given by Tatelman (p. 39) of the parallel Skt. phrase in the <hi rend="italic">Divyāvadāna</hi>: <hi rend="italic">apāyān kiṃ na paśyasi</hi>. See the Tib. trans. <hi rend="italic">ngan song la phyi’i phyir mi gzigs</hi>.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.34">“Son,” she said, “you speak harshly. Confess your transgression as a transgression,<note place="end">The “transgression” here would seem to be a transgression of the cultural expectation that a child address their parents with respect.</note> then its karma will dwindle, and be exhausted and spent.” </p>
                            <p n="1.34">Confessing his transgression as a transgression, he asked her forgiveness.</p>
                            <p n="1.35">Then, having performed the rituals for an auspicious, fortunate, and successful journey, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa packed many goods into carts, loads, sacks, and baskets, and onto camels, oxen, and donkeys, and set out for the great sea. Gradually passing through towns, cities, suburbs, and marketplaces, they arrived at the shore of the great sea, where they procured a large and splendid seafaring ship, in which they took to the great sea to procure wealth. Driven by a favorable wind, they reached the Isle of Jewels. After searching here and there, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa filled the great ship with jewels as if they were sesame seeds, grains, jujube berries, and kulattha peas. Driven by a favorable wind, the great ship returned to Jambudvīpa without mishap, and the merchants set up camp on the shore of the sea.</p>
                            <p n="1.36">Śṛoṇa Koṭīkarṇa took Dāsaka and Pālaka off to one side away from the caravan and began to calculate income and expenses.<note place="end">The Sanskrit varies from the Tibetan here, identifying Śroṇa as the caravan leader, as implied in his father’s announcement of the journey. It also establishes more clearly that he and Dāsaka and Pālaka had gone away from the caravan (<hi rend="italic">asau śroṇaḥ koṭīkarṇo ’pi sārthavāho dāsakapālakāv ādāya sārthamadhyād ekānte ’pakramya āyaṃ vyayaṃ ca tulayitum ārabdhaḥ</hi>).</note> Sometime later, he said to Dāsaka, “Dāsaka, see what the merchants are doing.” After he went there and saw that the merchants were sleeping, he lay down to sleep there too.</p>
                            <p n="1.37">When Dāsaka had been gone for a long time, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa said to Pālaka, “Pālaka, see what the merchants are doing.” After he went there and saw that the merchants were loading the pack animals, he began loading the pack animals too. </p>
                            <p n="1.37">Dāsaka thought, “I’m sure Pālaka will send for the caravan leader.” </p>
                            <p n="1.37">Pālaka thought, “I’m sure Dāsaka will send for the caravan leader.”</p>
                            <p n="1.38">After loading the pack animals, the merchants set off. </p>
                            <p n="1.38">Meanwhile, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, having grown drowsy, fell asleep.</p>
                            <p n="1.39">After setting out and traveling until daybreak, the merchants asked, “Gentlemen, where is the caravan leader?” </p>
                            <p n="1.39">“The caravan leader has gone to the front.”</p>
                            <p n="1.40">They went to the front and asked, “Where is the caravan leader?” </p>
                            <p n="1.40">“He went to the rear.”</p>
                            <p n="1.41">They went to the rear and asked, “Where is the caravan leader?” </p>
                            <p n="1.41">“He went to the middle.”</p>
                            <p n="1.42">They went to the middle and again asked, but he did not appear to be anywhere. </p>
                            <p n="1.42">Dāsaka said, “My thought was that Pālaka would surely send for the caravan leader.”</p>
                            <p n="1.43">Pālaka said, “My thought was that Dāsaka would surely send for the caravan leader. Gentlemen, in any event, we have left the caravan leader behind and that is not good, so come, let us go back!”</p>
                            <p n="1.44">“Gentlemen,” they said, “if we turn back, we will suffer all manner of misfortune, so come, let us just make a pact that, until our goods are stored away, on no account is anyone to inform Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s parents.” Having made such a pact, they carried on.</p>
                            <p n="1.45">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s parents, hearing that Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa was coming, went to welcome him.</p>
                            <p n="1.46">“Where is the caravan leader?” </p>
                            <p n="1.46">“He has gone to the front.”</p>
                            <p n="1.47">They went to the front and asked, “Where is the caravan leader?” </p>
                            <p n="1.47">“He went to the rear.”</p>
                            <p n="1.48">They went to the rear and asked, “Where is the caravan leader?” </p>
                            <p n="1.48">“He went to the middle.”</p>
                            <p n="1.49">They confused the couple until the goods were stored away and then said, “Father, mother, we forgot the caravan leader.”</p>
                            <p n="1.50">Later, someone came to the parents and said, “Father, mother, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa has come!” The parents gave him a reward and went to welcome Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, but did not see him. Yet another person came and said, “Father, mother, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa has come!” They gave him a reward and went to welcome their son but saw no sign of him. Thus they came to trust no one.</p>
                            <p n="1.51">In gardens, temples, and pavilions they placed parasols, bells, and fans on which they wrote, “If Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa still lives, may he quickly return, may he swiftly return! If he has passed away and gone to another life, may he be reborn into an exceptional life.” The couple went blind from grief and sobbing.</p>
                            <p n="1.52">Meanwhile, when Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa woke up at sunrise, touched by the sun’s rays, he saw just two donkeys and not a single merchant there. He yoked and drove the two donkeys onward. As they went along, a wind blew up and covered the path with sand. Since the donkeys could remember the way, sniffing at the path, they proceeded slowly along. But when he hit and drove them with his spiked rod, he disturbed their memory and they strayed from the path into a forest of śāla trees.</p>
                            <p n="1.53">When he saw the two donkeys overcome by thirst, tongues hanging out, both confused, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa felt compassion. He thought, “If I don’t set them free, they shall suffer all manner of misfortune with me.”</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa in the City of Hungry Ghosts</head>
                            <p n="1.54">So he freed them both and walked on until he saw a high and broad city of iron, at the gate of which stood a man, dark black, intimidating, fierce, red eyed, with a massive body, holding an iron club in his hand.<note place="end">The translation follows the more complete Sanskrit here: <hi rend="italic">tatra dvāre puruṣas tiṣṭhati kālo raudraś caṇḍo lohitākṣa udbaddha­piṇḍo lohalaguḍavya­grahastaḥ</hi>.</note> Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa approached him and said, “Hey, my good man!<note place="end">The Tibetan has Śroṇa hail this person as <hi rend="italic">nang rje</hi> (“master of the house,” i.e., “husband”), whereas the Sanskrit has Śroṇa hail him simply as <hi rend="italic">puruṣa</hi> (“man” or “friend”). “Good man” seems a happy medium as a friendly address that is neither too formal nor too casual.</note> Is there any water here?” </p>
                            <p n="1.54">He just stood there silently, without saying a word.</p>
                            <p n="1.55">Śroṇa asked again, “Hey, my good man! Is there any water here?” </p>
                            <p n="1.55">But the man still stood there silently, without saying a word.</p>
                            <p n="1.56">Śroṇa entered the city, calling out, “Water! Water!” whereupon he was surrounded by many hundreds of thousands of hungry ghosts with bodies resembling scorched posts, bone contraptions draped with head and body hair, with stomachs resembling mountains, and mouths like the eye of a needle. </p>
                            <p n="1.56">“O Śroṇa, you are compassionate!” they said. “We are thirsty. Pour us some water.”</p>
                            <p n="1.57">“Gentlemen,” he replied, “I too am looking for water. Where is there water that I can give you?” </p>
                            <p n="1.57">“Śroṇa, where would there be water in this city of hungry ghosts?” they said. “In the past twelve years, only today have we heard the words ‘water, water.’ ”</p>
                            <p n="1.58">“Gentlemen, who are you and what deed caused you to be born here?” </p>
                            <p n="1.58">“Śroṇa, the people of Jambudvīpa are skeptical, so you won’t believe us.”</p>
                            <p n="1.59">“Gentlemen, how could I not believe you when I can see you with my own eyes?” </p>
                            <p n="1.59">Then they uttered this verse:</p>
                            <lg n="1.60">
                                <l>“We spoke harshly, we were angry, We were miserly and avaricious, We made not the least little donation, And so we have arrived in the realm of hungry ghosts.</l>
                            </lg>
                            <p n="1.61">“Śroṇa, you possess very powerful merit, so go! Have you seen anyone at all who has entered a city of hungry ghosts and left it alive?”</p>
                            <p n="1.62">He departed, and when he saw the man he said to him, “Alas, my friend! Had you informed me that this is a city of hungry ghosts, I would not have entered it.”</p>
                            <p n="1.63">The man replied, “Śroṇa, you possess very powerful merit, so go! Have you seen anyone at all who has entered a city of hungry ghosts and left it alive?”<note place="end">In the Tibetan text, the man at the gate merely repeats the words used by the hungry ghosts. The Sanskrit text makes better sense; the man points out that Śroṇa has indeed come out of the city alive because of his great merit: <hi rend="italic">puṇya­maheśākhyas tvam*/ yena tvaṃ pretanagaraṃ praviśya svastikṣemābhyāṃ nirgataḥ</hi>.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.64">Some time after he departed, Śroṇa saw another high and broad city of iron, at the gate of which stood a man, dark black, intimidating, fierce, red eyed, with a massive body, holding an iron club in his hand . He approached the man and said “Hey, my good man! Is there any water here?” </p>
                            <p n="1.64">He just stood there, without saying a word.</p>
                            <p n="1.65">“Hey, my good man! Is there any water here?” he asked again. </p>
                            <p n="1.65">But the man still stood there, without saying a word.</p>
                            <p n="1.66">Śroṇa entered the city, calling out, “Water! Water!” whereupon he was surrounded by many hundreds of thousands of hungry ghosts with bodies resembling scorched posts, bone contraptions draped with head and body hair, with stomachs resembling mountains, and mouths like the eye of a needle. </p>
                            <p n="1.66">“O Śroṇa, you are compassionate!” they said. “We are thirsty. Pour us some water.”</p>
                            <p n="1.67">“Gentlemen,” he said, “I too am looking for water. Where is there water that I can give you?” </p>
                            <p n="1.67">“Śroṇa, where would there be water in this city of hungry ghosts?” they said. “In the past twelve years, only today have we heard the words ‘water, water’ from you.”</p>
                            <p n="1.68">“Gentlemen, who are you and what deed caused you to be born here?” </p>
                            <p n="1.68">They replied, “Śroṇa, the people of Jambudvīpa are skeptical, so you won’t believe us.”</p>
                            <p n="1.69">“Gentlemen, how can I not believe you when I can see you with my own eyes?” </p>
                            <p n="1.69">Then they uttered this verse:</p>
                            <lg n="1.70">
                                <l>“Drunk with the conceit of good health, Drunk with the arrogance of youth and wealth, We made no donations at all, And so we have arrived in the realm of hungry ghosts.</l>
                            </lg>
                            <p n="1.71">“Śroṇa, you possess very powerful merit, so go! Have you seen anyone at all who has entered a city of hungry ghosts and left it alive?” </p>
                            <p n="1.71">He departed, and when he saw the man he said to him, “Alas, my friend! If you had informed me that this is a city of hungry ghosts, I would not have entered it.”</p>
                            <p n="1.72">The man replied, “Śroṇa, you possess very powerful merit, so go! Have you seen anyone at all who has entered a city of hungry ghosts and left it alive?”</p>
                            <p n="1.73">He departed and some time later, when the sun was setting, he saw a heavenly palace.<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">gzhal med khang</hi>, literally “an inconceivable dwelling.” Skt. <hi rend="italic">vimāna</hi> usually refers to a flying mansion or palace.</note> In it there were four well-formed apsarā nymphs, beautiful and pleasing to the eye, and a well-formed man, handsome and pleasing to the eye, who was adorned with armlets, earrings, bracelets, perfumes, and all kinds of garlands. Alone, he played with, took pleasure in, and amused the apsarā nymphs.</p>
                            <p n="1.74">Seeing him while he was still far away, they each began to call out, “Welcome, Śroṇa! Are you not thirsty? Are you not hungry?”</p>
                            <p n="1.75">Thinking, “Without a doubt they are gods, or nāgas, or yakṣas,” he replied, “I am thirsty. I am hungry.”</p>
                            <p n="1.76">They bathed him and gave him food, and he remained in the heavenly palace until the sun was about to rise. They said to him, “Śroṇa, it will be miserable here, so leave.”</p>
                            <p n="1.77">Śroṇa left, went a short distance in one direction, and waited. Then, later, when the sun rose, the heavenly palace vanished. The apsarā nymphs vanished too. A pack of four piebald dogs appeared. They knocked the man over and, tearing at the flesh and skin of his back in mouthfuls, they fed on them until sunset.</p>
                            <p n="1.78">Then the heavenly palace reappeared. The apsarā nymphs also reappeared, and the well-formed man, handsome and pleasing to the eye, who was adorned with armlets, earrings, bracelets, perfumes, and all kinds of garlands, played with, took pleasure in, and amused the apsarā nymphs.</p>
                            <p n="1.79">Śroṇa approached them and asked, “Good people, who are you and what deed caused you to be born here?” </p>
                            <p n="1.79">“Śroṇa, the people of Jambudvīpa are skeptical, so you won’t believe us.”</p>
                            <p n="1.80">“Good people, how can I not believe you when I can see you with my own eyes?” </p>
                            <p n="1.80">“Śroṇa, when I was a butcher in the village of Vāsava I earned my living by slaughtering sheep and selling their meat. Out of compassion the noble Mahākātyāyana came to see me and said, ‘My friend, the ripening fruit of this behavior will be unpleasant, so give up this evil, unworthy way of life.’</p>
                            <p n="1.81">“But I did not give it up as he had urged. To persuade me to give it up, again and again he said, ‘My friend, the ripening fruit of this behavior will be unpleasant, so give up this evil, unworthy way of life.’</p>
                            <p n="1.82">“But I still did not give it up. Then he asked me, ‘My friend, do you slaughter the sheep during the day or at night?’ </p>
                            <p n="1.82">“ ‘During the day, noble one,’ I replied.</p>
                            <p n="1.83">“He said, ‘Why not pledge to observe pure conduct at night?’ </p>
                            <p n="1.83">“After that I pledged to observe pure conduct at night. The ripening fruit of that act is that I experience pleasure in this way at night, while the ripening fruit of the act of slaughtering sheep by day is that I experience suffering in this way during the day.” </p>
                            <p n="1.83">Then he uttered this verse:</p>
                            <lg n="1.84">
                                <l>“By day I took the lives of others, By night my conduct was virtuous. The good and evil fruits of those acts Are what I experience here.</l>
                            </lg>
                            <p n="1.85">“Śroṇa, are you going to the village of Vāsava? Tell my son, who works as a butcher there, ‘I saw your father, and he says the ripening fruit of this work will be unpleasant, so give up this evil, unworthy way of life.’</p>
                            <p n="1.86">“Alas, my good man, as you have said to me, the people of Jambudvīpa are skeptical. He won’t believe me.”</p>
                            <p n="1.87">“Śroṇa, if he doesn’t believe you, tell him, ‘Your father says that he buried a pot of gold dust beneath the butchering block. Retrieve it and live in happiness and contentment for a long time. From time to time offer alms to the noble Mahākātyāyana, and dedicate the merit in our name. Then the karma will dwindle, and be exhausted and spent.”</p>
                            <p n="1.88">Śroṇa departed and, some time later, when the sun was rising, he saw another heavenly palace. In it there was a well-formed apsarā nymph, beautiful and pleasing to the eye, and a well-formed man, handsome and pleasing to the eye, who was adorned with armlets, earrings, bracelets, perfumes, and all kinds of garlands. He frolicked, took pleasure, and made love with her.</p>
                            <p n="1.89">Seeing him while he was still far away, they each began to call out, “Welcome, Śroṇa! Are you not thirsty? Are you not hungry?” </p>
                            <p n="1.89">Thinking, “Without a doubt they are gods, or nāgas, or yakṣas,” he said, “I am thirsty. I am hungry.”</p>
                            <p n="1.90">They bathed him and gave him food, and he remained in the heavenly palace until sunset when they said to him, “Śroṇa, it will be miserable here, so leave.”</p>
                            <p n="1.91">Śroṇa, who had seen other miseries, left, went a short distance in one direction, and waited. Then, at sunset, the heavenly palace vanished. The apsarā nymph vanished too. A great centipede appeared. It wrapped itself seven times around the man’s body, winding up on top, from where it made a meal of his brains until the sun rose. [B21]</p>
                            <p n="1.92">Then the heavenly palace reappeared. The apsarā nymph also reappeared, as did the well-formed man, handsome and pleasing to the eye, who was adorned with armlets, earrings, bracelets, perfumes, and all kinds of garlands. He frolicked, took pleasure, and made love with her.</p>
                            <p n="1.93">Śroṇa approached them and asked, “Good people, who are you and what deed caused you to be born here?” </p>
                            <p n="1.93">“Śroṇa, the people of Jambudvīpa are skeptical, so you won’t believe us.”</p>
                            <p n="1.94">“How can I not believe you when I can see you with my own eyes?” </p>
                            <p n="1.94">The man said, “Śroṇa, when I was a brahmin in the village of Vāsava I committed adultery. Out of compassion the noble Mahākātyāyana came to see me and said, ‘My friend, the ripening fruit of this behavior will be unpleasant, so give up this evil, unworthy way of life.’</p>
                            <p n="1.95">“But I did not give it up as he had urged. To persuade me to give it up, again and again he said, ‘My friend, the ripening fruit of this behavior will be unpleasant, so give up this evil, unworthy way of life.’</p>
                            <p n="1.96">“But I still did not give it up. He said to me, ‘My friend, do you commit adultery during the day or at night?’ </p>
                            <p n="1.96">“ ‘Noble one, at night,’ I replied.</p>
                            <p n="1.97">“He said, ‘My friend, why not pledge to observe pure conduct during the day? Then the karma will dwindle, and be exhausted and spent.’</p>
                            <p n="1.98">“After that I pledged to observe pure conduct during the day. The ripening fruit of that act of accepting moral precepts properly and observing them during the day is that I experience pleasure in this way during the day, while the ripening fruit of the act of committing adultery at night is that I experience suffering in this way at night.” </p>
                            <p n="1.98">Then he uttered this verse:</p>
                            <lg n="1.99">
                                <l>“By night I committed adultery with passion, By day my conduct was virtuous. The good and evil fruits of those acts Are what I experience here.</l>
                            </lg>
                            <p n="1.100">“Śroṇa, are you going to the village of Vāsava? Tell my son, who is a brahmin who commits adultery there, ‘I saw your father, and he says the ripening fruit of this behavior will be unpleasant, so give up this evil, unworthy way of life.’</p>
                            <p n="1.101">Śroṇa replied, “Alas, my good man, as you have said, the people of Jambudvīpa are skeptical. He won’t believe me.”</p>
                            <p n="1.102">“Śroṇa, if he doesn’t believe you, tell him, ‘Your father says that he buried a pot of gold dust beneath the hearth. Retrieve it and live in happiness and contentment for a long time. And from time to time offer alms to the noble Mahākātyāyana and dedicate the merit in our name. Then the karma will dwindle, and be exhausted and spent.”</p>
                            <p n="1.103">Śroṇa departed and, some time later, when the sun was rising, he saw another heavenly palace. In it a well-formed woman, beautiful and pleasing to the eye, who was adorned with armlets, earrings, bracelets, perfumes, and all kinds of garlands, lay on a bed with four hungry ghosts tied to the four bedposts. Seeing him while he was still far away, she called out, “Welcome, Śroṇa! Are you not thirsty? Are you not hungry?”</p>
                            <p n="1.104">Thinking, “Without a doubt they are gods, or nāgas, or yakṣas,” he said, “I am thirsty. I am hungry.”</p>
                            <p n="1.105">She bathed him and gave him food, and said, “Śroṇa, if these ghosts beg anything from you, do not give it!”</p>
                            <p n="1.106">Wishing to know for himself what deeds those beings had done, he entered the heavenly palace and waited. They began to beg, “Śroṇa, you are compassionate! Give us something‍—we’re terribly hungry!”</p>
                            <p n="1.107">The small bit he gave to one turned to chaff. He gave a bit to another one and it turned into an iron ball as it ate it. He gave a bit to yet another one and it turned into its own flesh as it ate it. And he gave a bit to another one and it turned to pus and blood.</p>
                            <p n="1.108">At the smell of that, the woman appeared and said, “Śroṇa, did I not forbid you? Why have you given things to them? Is your compassion greater than my compassion?”</p>
                            <p n="1.109">“Sister, who are these people to you?” he asked. </p>
                            <p n="1.109">She replied, “This is my husband, this is my son, this is my daughter-in-law, and this, my serving girl.”</p>
                            <p n="1.110">“Who are you all and what deed caused you to be born here?” </p>
                            <p n="1.110">“Śroṇa, the people of Jambudvīpa are skeptical, so you won’t believe us.”</p>
                            <p n="1.111">“Sister, how can I not believe you when I can see you with my own eyes?” </p>
                            <p n="1.111">The lady said, “Śroṇa, when I was a brahmin woman in the village of Vāsava, I prepared fine foods on the eve of a particular auspicious constellation. Out of compassion for me, the noble Mahākātyāyana came to the village of Vāsava on his alms round and gradually made his way to my house. I saw him, with his gracious body and serene mind. Seeing him, I was filled with faith, and full of faith in him, I offered him alms.</p>
                            <p n="1.112">“I had the thought, ‘I shall give my husband the opportunity to share in my joy!’ He bathed and came in, and I said to him, ‘Rejoice, master, for I have offered alms to the noble Mahākātyāyana.’</p>
                            <p n="1.113">“He became angry and said, ‘While we do not give to brahmins nor do we show kinship honors to kin, you offer the best of alms to that bald-headed ascetic!’ Growing indignant, he shouted, ‘Why doesn’t that bald-headed ascetic eat chaff!’ The ripening fruit of that act means he has to eat chaff.</p>
                            <p n="1.114">“I had the thought, ‘Since my husband did not share in my joy, I shall give my son the opportunity to share in my joy!’ I said to him as well, ‘Rejoice, my son, for I have offered alms to the noble Mahākātyāyana.’</p>
                            <p n="1.115">“He also became angry and said, ‘While we do not give to brahmins nor do we show kinship honors to kin, you offer the best of alms to that bald-headed ascetic!’ Growing indignant, he shouted, ‘Why doesn’t that bald-headed ascetic eat an iron ball!’ The ripening fruit of that act means that he has to eat an iron ball.</p>
                            <p n="1.116">“Śroṇa, on the eve of a particular auspicious constellation, my kin sent me some baked treats. When I entrusted them to my daughter-in-law, she ate the freshest of the baked treats and gave the lesser ones to me. I sent a message to those friends: ‘Are you having a bad harvest? You sent such poor baked treats to me.’</p>
                            <p n="1.117">“They sent a message back, saying, ‘We did not send you poor baked treats; on the contrary, we sent you the best baked treats!’</p>
                            <p n="1.118">“So I said to my daughter-in-law, ‘Young lady, you ate the best of the baked treats and gave the lesser ones to me, did you not?’ </p>
                            <p n="1.118">“She replied, ‘If I ate your baked treats, why ought I not eat my own flesh?’ The ripening fruit of that act means that she has to eat her own flesh.</p>
                            <p n="1.119">“On the eve of a particular auspicious constellation, I handed our serving girl some baked treats and sent her off to my kin. She ate some of the baked treats along the way and gave them lesser ones. They sent me a message, saying, ‘Are you having a bad harvest? You sent us such poor baked treats.’</p>
                            <p n="1.120">“I sent a message back: ‘I did not send you poor baked treats; on the contrary, I sent you the best baked treats!’ </p>
                            <p n="1.120">“I asked the maidservant, ‘Girl, you ate the best of the baked treats and gave the lesser ones to them, didn’t you?’</p>
                            <p n="1.121">“She replied, ‘If I ate your fine food, why ought I not drink pus and blood?’ The ripening fruit of that act means she has to drink pus and blood.</p>
                            <p n="1.122">“I had the thought, ‘May I be reborn in a place where I can see these beings experience the fruits of their own actions.’ Because of all the alms I have offered to the noble Mahākātyāyana, I should have been reborn in the blessed Heaven of the Thirty-Three.<note place="end">The Heaven of the Thirty-Three Gods, situated according to ancient Indian cosmology above the realm of the four heavenly kings.</note> But because I made a perverse wish, I have now been reborn as a powerful hungry ghost.</p>
                            <p n="1.123">“Śroṇa, if you go again to the village of Vāsava, tell my daughter, who works as a prostitute there, ‘I saw your father, mother, elder brother, sister-in-law, and serving girl, and they say that the ripening fruit of this behavior will be unpleasant, so give up this evil, unworthy way of life.’ ”</p>
                            <p n="1.124">“Sister, as you have said, the people of Jambudvīpa are skeptical. She won’t believe me.”</p>
                            <p n="1.125">She replied, “Śroṇa, if she doesn’t believe you, tell her, ‘In your father’s former home there are four pairs of iron cauldrons filled with gold, and among them there is a golden staff and water jug. Retrieve them and live in happiness and contentment for a long time. From time to time offer alms to the noble Mahākātyāyana and dedicate the merit in our name. Then the karma will dwindle, and be exhausted and spent.’ ”</p>
                            <p n="1.126">He promised to do as she said. </p>
                            <p n="1.126">Twelve years passed as he wandered in that way.</p>
                            <p n="1.127">The lady asked him, “Śroṇa, will you go to the village of Vāsava?” </p>
                            <p n="1.127">“Sister, I will go,” he replied, and entered the heavenly palace.</p>
                            <p n="1.128">She instructed the hungry ghosts, “Good people, today, as Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa sleeps, place him in his father’s garden in the village of Vāsava and come back.” They placed him in his father’s garden in the village of Vāsava.</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa Returns to the Village of Vāsava</head>
                            <p n="1.129">As soon as Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa woke, he saw offerings of bells, parasols, and fans on which had been written, “If Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa still lives, may he quickly return, may he swiftly return! If he has passed away and gone to another life, may he be reborn into an exceptional life.” He reflected, “If my father and mother consider me dead, why should I re-enter household life? I will leave and go forth in the presence of the noble Mahākātyāyana.”</p>
                            <p n="1.130">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa then went to where the venerable Mahākātyāyana was staying. The venerable Mahākātyāyana saw Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa while he was still far away. On seeing him he said to Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, “Come, Śroṇa! Welcome, Śroṇa! Śroṇa, have you seen this world and what is beyond this world?”</p>
                            <p n="1.131">“Venerable Mahākātyāyana, I’ve seen them. If you permit it, honorable Mahākātyāyana, I would receive the going forth, ordination, and monkhood in the well-spoken Dharma and Vinaya. I would live the holy life in the presence of the Blessed One.”<note place="end">This is ambiguous. The Tibetan epithet <hi rend="italic">bcom ldan ’das</hi> is most often used for the Buddha himself, whereas the Sanskrit <hi rend="italic">bhagavat</hi> (here in the genitive: <hi rend="italic">bhagavato ’ntike</hi>) is frequently used for great teachers, such as Mahākātyāyana. Śroṇa does later ask for leave to go to see the Buddha, so perhaps he is already voicing that ambition here.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.132">“Śroṇa, just remember your prior pledges. First, convey the messages you have been given.”</p>
                            <p n="1.133">Śroṇa went to the butcher and said to him, “My friend, I saw your father, and he says the ripening fruit of this behavior will be unpleasant, so give up this evil, unworthy way of life!”</p>
                            <p n="1.134">“Ah, my good man!” he replied, “Twelve years have passed since my father died. Have you seen someone who has returned from beyond this world?”</p>
                            <p n="1.135">“My friend, I have been there.” </p>
                            <p n="1.135">He did not believe him.</p>
                            <p n="1.136">“My friend, if you do not believe me, your father says that he buried a pot of gold dust beneath his butchering block. Retrieve it and live in happiness and contentment for a long time. From time to time offer alms to the noble Mahākātyāyana and dedicate the merit in his name. Then the karma will dwindle, and be exhausted and spent.”</p>
                            <p n="1.137">He reflected, “I have never heard anything like this before. First I will take a look‍—if it is really so, then everything he said is true.” He went there and dug until he saw it. Everything was just as Śroṇa had said. Then he believed.</p>
                            <p n="1.138">After that, Śroṇa approached the adulterer and said to him, “My friend, I saw your father, and he says the ripening fruit of this behavior will be unpleasant, so give up this evil, unworthy way of life!”</p>
                            <p n="1.139">“Ah, my good man!” he replied, “Twelve years have passed since my father died. Have you seen someone who has returned from beyond this world?” </p>
                            <p n="1.139">“My friend, I have been there.” </p>
                            <p n="1.139">He did not believe him.</p>
                            <p n="1.140">Śroṇa said, “My friend, if you do not believe me, your father says that he buried a pot of gold dust beneath the hearth. Retrieve it and live in happiness and contentment for a long time. From time to time offer alms to the noble Mahākātyāyana and dedicate the merit in his name. Then the karma will dwindle, and be exhausted and spent.”</p>
                            <p n="1.141">He reflected, “I have never heard anything like this before. First I will take a look‍—if it is really so, then everything he said is true.” He went there and dug until he saw it. Everything was just as he had said. Then he believed.</p>
                            <p n="1.142">After that, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa approached the prostitute and said to her, “Sister, I saw your father, mother, elder brother, sister-in-law, and serving girl, and they say the ripening fruit of this behavior will be unpleasant, so give up this evil, unworthy way of life.”</p>
                            <p n="1.143">“Ah, my good man!” she replied, “Twelve years have passed since my father and mother died. Have you seen someone who has returned from beyond this world?” </p>
                            <p n="1.143">He said, “I have been there.” </p>
                            <p n="1.143">She did not believe him.</p>
                            <p n="1.144">He said, “Sister, if you don’t believe me, your mother says that in your father’s former home there are four pairs of iron cauldrons filled with gold, and among them there is a golden staff and water pitcher. Retrieve them and live in happiness and contentment for a long time. From time to time offer alms to the noble Mahākātyāyana and dedicate the merit in their name. Then the karma will dwindle, and be exhausted and spent.”</p>
                            <p n="1.145">She reflected, “I have never heard anything like this before. First I will take a look‍—if it really is so, then everything he said is true.” She went there and dug until she saw it all. Everything was just as he had said. Then she believed.</p>
                            <p n="1.146">Thinking, “All these worldly beings believe in gold, but no one believed in me,” Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa smiled. As a child, his teeth had been embellished with gold. Recognizing them, she asked, “Are you the caravan leader Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa?” </p>
                            <p n="1.146">“Sister, people know me as such.”</p>
                            <p n="1.147">The prostitute departed and reported to his parents, “Father, mother, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa has come!” But as many had also brought such reports, they did not believe it, until some time later when he himself came and said, “Father and mother, I pay my respects to you.” As he had a golden timbre, they recognized him from his voice, threw their arms around his neck, and began to cry. Their falling tears washed the cataracts from their eyes, and they began to see.</p>
                            <p n="1.148">He said, “Father, Mother, please grant me permission to go forth from the household life into homelessness, for I have faith in only what is perfect. ”</p>
                            <p n="1.149">The couple replied, “Son, weeping with grief over you, we went blind. Now that you have come, our sight is restored. So long as we live, do not go forth. But when we are dead, go forth then.”</p>
                            <p n="1.150">Hearing the Dharma from the venerable Mahākātyāyana, he realized the fruit of stream entry.<note place="end">Tibetan: <hi rend="italic">rgyun du zhugs pa’i ’bras bu</hi>; Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit form: <hi rend="italic">srota-āpattiphala</hi>. The first in a sequence of stages on the path to becoming an arhat (the fourth stage).</note> His father and mother also went for refuge<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">skyabs su ’gro ba</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">śaraṇāgamana</hi>. The ritual of seeking refuge in the Three Jewels (the Buddha, Dharma, and Saṅgha), available for lay people.</note> and were established in the training precepts.<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">bslab pa’i gzhi rnams</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">śikṣāpada</hi>. There are many precepts for novices, monks, and nuns, but five basic rules apply to all Buddhists, including the laity: to abstain from killing, stealing, sexual misconduct, false speech, and intoxicants.</note> He understood the four āgamas<note place="end">The four collections of sūtras or “discourses” given by the Buddha (and also some of the great disciples): Long Discourses, Middle-Length Discourses, Connected Discourses, and Numerical Discourses; known as the Nikāyas in the Theravādin (Pali) tradition. The contents of the various collections varied between the different early schools of Buddhism. The Degé here has <hi rend="italic">lung bzhin</hi> while Stok Palace has <hi rend="italic">lung gzhi</hi>. However, the Sanskrit makes it clear that Śroṇa understood the “four collections,” i.e. <hi rend="italic">lung bzhi</hi>: <hi rend="italic">āgama­catuṣṭayam adhītam*</hi>.</note> and realized the fruit of once-returning.<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">lan gcig phyir ’ong ba’i ’bras bu</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">sakṛdāgāmi­phala</hi>. The second stage on the path to arhatship. This person will only be reborn once more in this world before achieving enlightenment.</note> His father and mother were also established in the truths.<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">bden pa rnams</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">satyāni</hi>. The four noble truths, viz., the universality of suffering, the cause of suffering, the truth that suffering can end, and the eightfold path that leads to nirvāṇa.</note></p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa Becomes a Monk</head>
                            <p n="1.151">Some time later, his father and mother passed away. Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa gave his riches to the poor, to widows and orphans, the needy and the destitute. Having given mostly to the needy,<note place="end">“The needy” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">bkren pa</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">daridra</hi>). Note that this term can also imply “the hungry.” The translation here follows the Tibetan: <hi rend="italic">bkren pa phal mo che zhig dbul bor</hi>. For comparison, the Sanskrit translates as “having made the needy not needy” (Skt. <hi rend="italic">daridrān adaridrān krtvā</hi>).</note> he went to the venerable Mahākātyāyana and, having bowed his head at the venerable Mahākātyāyana’s feet, sat to one side. While seated to one side, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa said to the venerable Mahākātyāyana, “Noble Mahākātyāyana, if you permit it, I would receive the going forth, ordination, and monkhood in the well-spoken Dharma and Vinaya. I would live the holy life in the presence of the Blessed One.”</p>
                            <p n="1.152">The venerable Mahākātyāyana allowed him to go forth, and he learned the mātṛkā and realized the fruit of non-returning.<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">phyir mi ’ong ba’i ’bras bu</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">anāgāmiphala</hi>. The third stage on the path to arhatship. Non-returners will not be reborn in this world; they will either attain arhatship in their present lifetime or they will be reborn in a heavenly realm where they will achieve their goal.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.153">As the company of monks in the frontier country of Aśmaka was only small, and it was difficult to fill a gathering of ten for an assembly,<note place="end">A minimum of ten monks is generally required to perform the formal acts of ordination.</note> Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa remained a novice for three months.</p>
                            <p n="1.154">As a rule, the disciples of blessed buddhas hold two assemblies: the great assembly, in the summer month of Āṣāḍha at the onset of the rainy season,<note place="end">The rainy season lasted from June until October. Buddhist monks and nuns spent this time in retreat in one place. The month of Āṣāḍha (Tib. <hi rend="italic">dbyar zla ’bring po</hi>) corresponds roughly to the latter part of June and the first part of July. See <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on the Rains</hi> (<hi rend="italic">Varṣāvastu</hi>, Toh 1-4) for more.</note> and on the full moon of the autumnal month of Kārtika.<note place="end">The month of Kārtika (Tib. <hi rend="italic">ston zla ’bring po</hi>) lasts from late October to early November.</note> Those who gather in the summer month of Āṣāḍha at the onset of the rainy season take up instructions, yoga, and attention, and, having mastered them,<note place="end">The translation here follows the Sanskrit (<hi rend="italic">uddeśa­yoga­manasikārān udgṛhya paryavāpya</hi>). The Tibetan, which is less specific, translates as “grasp this and that particular of attention and having mastered”: <hi rend="italic">yid la byed pa’i khyad par de dang de dag bzung nas chub par byas te</hi>.</note> pledge to spend the rainy season in villages, cities, towns, territories, and royal capitals. Those who gather on the full moon of the autumnal month of Kārtika report their understandings and ask questions on outstanding matters.<note place="end">Where <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> reads generically “outstanding matters,” the <hi rend="italic">Divyāvadāna</hi> spells out that this refers to sūtra, vinaya, and mātṛkā. Together, these two assemblies appear to represent gatherings for meditation and recitation (or “scriptural study”), respectively.</note> The great disciples did this as well.<note place="end">The first phrase of this paragraph (“As a rule,”) asserts that this tradition of two gatherings is universally observed by all buddhas, while the last line asserts that, naturally, it was also observed by the Buddha Śākyamuni’s immediate disciples.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.155">Thus, the venerable Mahākātyāyana’s wards and apprentices took up instructions, yoga, and attention, and, having mastered them,<note place="end">The translation here follows the Sanskrit, as above.</note> pledged to spend the rainy season in villages, cities, towns, territories, and royal capitals. Having passed the three summer months, with their robes mended and ready, they took up their alms bowls and robes and went to the venerable Mahākātyāyana. Arriving there, they bowed their heads at the feet of the venerable Mahākātyāyana and sat to one side.</p>
                            <p n="1.156">They reported their understandings and asked questions on outstanding matters. Since a gathering of ten for an assembly could be filled, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa was ordained by them. After studying the Tripiṭaka, he uprooted all afflictions and realized arhatship. As an arhat, he was one free from desire for the three realms<note place="end">The three realms of existence in saṃsāra: the desire realm (Skt. <hi rend="italic">kāmadhātu</hi>), the form realm (Skt. <hi rend="italic">rūpadhātu</hi>), and the formless realm (Skt. <hi rend="italic">ārūpyadhātu</hi>).</note>, for whom a lump of clay was equal to gold, for whom space was equal to the palm of his hand, who accepted being cut by an adze and being anointed with sandalwood as the same, and whose knowledge had shattered the eggshell of ignorance. He attained insight, supernormal knowledge, and discerning wisdom; he turned his back on worldly profit, desires and honors; and he became an object of veneration, respect, and praise for the gods, including Indra<note place="end">The king of the gods, also known as Śakra.</note> and Upendra.</p>
                            <p n="1.157">The venerable Mahākātyāyana’s wards and apprentices paid their respects to him and said, “Preceptor, we have seen and attended you. Now we will go to attend the Blessed One.”</p>
                            <p n="1.158">“Do so, my sons. The ones thus gone, arhats, the complete and perfect buddhas should certainly be attended.”</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa Visits the Buddha</head>
                            <p n="1.159">At that time, it happened that Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa had joined the assembly and was sitting in its midst. Then the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa rose from his seat and arranged his upper robe on one shoulder, knelt with his right knee on the ground, and said to the venerable Mahākātyāyana, “I have seen you, preceptor, and I have experienced the Blessed One’s Dharma body as well. But since I have not seen his physical body, preceptor, I would go to see the Blessed One’s physical body.”</p>
                            <p n="1.160">“Do so, my son. It is rare to see the one thus gone, the arhat, the complete and perfect Buddha‍—as rare as a flower on an udumbara tree. Bow your head at the feet of the Blessed One on my behalf ask him if he is at ease, and so forth,<note place="end">A standard formula, abbreviated here, but see 1.169.</note> and then pose these five questions:<note place="end">In the following, Mahākātyāyana instructs Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa to ask the Buddha “five questions” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">zhu ba lnga bo</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">pañca praśnāni</hi>) but the third of these questions is omitted in both the Sanskrit and Tibetan texts. While the third question is never explicitly stated in the text, the Buddha addresses five issues in his response to Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, the third of which concerns sandals with lining. There on 1.180, the Buddha allows that sandals with a single lining but not a second or third lining may be kept and worn (Tib. <hi rend="italic">mchil lham rim gcig pa bcang bar bya ste / rim gnyis pa ma yin / rim gsum pa ma yin no</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">ekapalāśike upānahe dhārayitavye na dvipuṭe na tripuṭe</hi>). The section in which the Buddha allows sandals with a single lining can be found on 1.275.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.161">“Honorable One, as the company of monks in the frontier country of Aśmaka is only small, it is difficult to fill a gathering of ten for an assembly. What should I do about this?</p>
                            <p n="1.162">“Honorable One, the ground grows rough after it is trampled by cattle. In a place like the frontier country of Aśmaka, ground-spreads and ground-spread covers are made from sheepskin, cowhide, deerskin, and goatskin. Just as in other lands the ground-spreads and ground-spread covers are seats of wool, seats of tree bark, seats of cotton, and seats of cotton-wool mix, just so in the frontier country of Aśmaka, the ground-spreads and ground-spread covers are sheepskin, and so forth, as just mentioned. </p>
                            <p n="1.162">“The people, who wash with water, have a custom of taking ritual baths.</p>
                            <p n="1.163">“Who incurs an offense requiring forfeiture, if the robes sent by a monk to another monk are lost on their way from the starting point and do not reach the destination?”<note place="end">This refers presumably to the first of the thirty offenses requiring forfeiture (Skt. <hi rend="italic">naiḥsargikāḥ pātayantikāḥ</hi>; Tib. <hi rend="italic">spang ba’i ltung byed</hi>). The first of these offenses, abbreviated as Tib. <hi rend="italic">gos ’chang ba</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">cīvara</hi>, deals with keeping cloth that is not one’s own for ten days or more. The relevant offense is given in <hi rend="italic">The Prātimokṣa Sūtra</hi>, (Toh 2, F.8.a): Tib. <hi rend="italic">dge slong chos gos zin pas sra brkyang phyung na / zhag bcu’i bar du gos lhag pa rnams par ma brtags pa bcang bar bya’o // de las ’das par bcangs na spang ba’i ltung byed do</hi>. The Sanskrit original reads Skt. <hi rend="italic">niṣṭhitacīvareṇa bhikṣuṇā uddhṛte kaṭhine daśāha­paramaṃ atirekacīvaram avi­kalpitaṃ dhārayitavyaṃ tataḥ uttari dhārayen naisargikā pāyantikā</hi>.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.164">The venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa listened without speaking to the venerable Mahākātyāyana. Then the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa bowed his head at the feet of the venerable Mahākātyāyana and took his leave from the venerable Mahākātyāyana.</p>
                            <p n="1.165">When that very night had passed and morning come, the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa put on his lower garment and, taking his bowl and robe, went into the village of Vāsava for alms and then gradually made his way to Śrāvastī. Then, having put away his bowl and robe and washed his feet, the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa went to the Blessed One, and on arrival bowed his head at the feet of the Blessed One and sat to one side.</p>
                            <p n="1.166">Then the Blessed One said to the venerable Ānanda, “Go, Ānanda! Prepare a couch in one of the monastery buildings for the One Thus Gone and Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa.”</p>
                            <p n="1.167">The venerable Ānanda replied, “Honorable One, I shall do as you say.” Following the Blessed One’s order, he prepared a couch in one of the monastery buildings for the One Thus Gone and Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa. He went to the Blessed One, and on arrival said to the Blessed One, “Honorable One, I have prepared a couch for the One Thus Gone and Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa in one of the monastery buildings. Blessed One, it is time.”</p>
                            <p n="1.168">The Blessed One and Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa then went to the monastery building. Having washed his feet outside the monastery building, the Blessed One entered, sat down cross-legged with his back straight, and focused his recollection. The venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa also washed his feet outside the building, and, on entering, with his legs crossed and body straight, focused his recollection. The Blessed One and the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa passed the night in noble silence.</p>
                            <p n="1.169">Then, as dawn approached, the Blessed One said to the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, “Śroṇa, be confident in the Dharma I have declared. After perceiving it, I awoke to buddhahood.”</p>
                            <p n="1.170">At the invitation of the Blessed One, Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa then recited, in the deep timbre of the frontier country of Aśmaka, from <hi rend="italic">The Inspired Utterances</hi>,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">ched du brjod pa</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">Udāna</hi>. For this work and the others chanted by Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, see Lamotte 1988, 161–63.</note> <hi rend="italic">Passing to the Farther Shore</hi>,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">pha rol ’gro byed</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">Pārāyaṇa</hi>.</note> <hi rend="italic">Seeing the Truth</hi>,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">bden pa mthong ba</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">Satyadṛś</hi>.</note> <hi rend="italic">The Verses of Śaila</hi>,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">ri gnas kyi tshigs su bcad pa</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">Śailagāthā</hi>.</note> <hi rend="italic">The Verses of the Sage</hi>,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">thub pa’i tshigs su bcad pa</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">Munigāthā</hi>.</note> <hi rend="italic">The Verses of the Elders</hi>,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">gnas brtan gyi tshigs su bcad pa</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">Sthaviragāthā</hi>.</note> <hi rend="italic">The Verses of the Elder Nuns</hi>,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">gnas brtan ma’i tshigs su bcad pa</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">Sthavirīgāthā</hi>.</note> and <hi rend="italic">Sūtras Concerning the Goal</hi>.<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">don gyi tshoms kyi mdo sde dag</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">Artha­vargīyāṇi sūtrāṇi</hi>.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.171">When the Blessed One knew that Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa had finished speaking, he said to the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, “Good, Śroṇa, good. You have recited sweetly the Dharma that I have declared. After perceiving it, I awoke to buddhahood.”</p>
                            <p n="1.172">Then the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa thought to himself, “Now the time has come for me to deliver to the Blessed One the requests sent by my preceptor.”</p>
                            <p n="1.173">With this in mind, he rose from his seat, placed his upper robe over one shoulder, and with his palms pressed together, bowed in the direction of the Blessed One and said to the Blessed One, “Honorable One, in a village in the frontier country of Aśmaka called Vāsava lives the honorable Mahākātyāyana, my preceptor, and he bows with his head at the feet of the Blessed One. He asks after your health, whether you are free from trouble, free from disease, in good physical condition, healthy, strong, happy, and so at ease.”<note place="end">This passage is a standard formula. It is abbreviated in the Skt. MS, but the full Sanskrit form can be supplied from a similar passage in the <hi rend="italic">Divyāvadāna</hi> 156.13–15.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.174">The Blessed One said, “Śroṇa, may the monk Kātyāyana be happy! You should also relate in detail the five questions.”</p>
                            <p n="1.175">Then the Blessed One said to Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, “Śroṇa, since now is not the time for me to expound on this question, ask your questions in the presence of the saṅgha. That will be the time for expounding on what you ask.”</p>
                            <p n="1.176">The Blessed One rose early in the morning and sat down on the prepared seat in the midst of the saṅgha. Then the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, and so forth, up to sat to one side.</p>
                            <p n="1.177">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa said to the Blessed One, “Honorable One, in a village in the frontier country of Aśmaka called Vāsava lives the honorable Mahākātyāyana, my preceptor, and he bows at the feet of the Blessed One, and so forth, up to at ease.” </p>
                            <p n="1.177">He related in detail the five questions as above,<note place="end">See F.264.b.</note> up to “offense requiring forfeiture.”</p>
                            <p n="1.178">The Blessed One said, “I therefore allow that ordination in border regions may be done by a group of five monks that includes a vinaya holder. Monks may bathe regularly. Sandals with a single lining may be kept, but not with a second lining, and not a third. If they wear out, they should be patched and then worn. Leather may be kept. If the robes sent by a monk to another monk are lost on their way from the starting point and do not reach the destination, no one will be guilty of an offense requiring forfeiture.”</p>
                            <p n="1.179">The venerable Upāli said to the Blessed One, “Honorable One, the Blessed One has said ordination in the border regions may be done by a group of five monks that includes a vinaya holder. What is the heartland, and what are border regions?”</p>
                            <p n="1.180">“Upāli, in the east, on the eastern side of the town called Puṇḍravardhana,<note place="end">Also called Puṇḍavardhana, located in present-day West Bengal; see BHSD, p. 346; Rotman 2008, p. 400, n. 192.</note> there is a forest called Puṇḍrakakṣa. That is the border.<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">dbus</hi>; Skt. has <hi rend="italic">anta</hi>.</note> Beyond that are the border regions. In the south, on the far side of the town called Śarāvatī,<note place="end">Also called Sarāvatī; see BHSD, p. 583.</note> there is a river called Śarāvatī; that is the border. Beyond that are the border regions. In the west, the brahmin towns of Sthūṇa<note place="end">BHSD, p. 611.</note> and Upasthūṇa<note place="end">BHSD, p. 144.</note> are the border. Beyond that are the border regions. In the north, the mountain called Uśīragiri<note place="end">Pali Usiraddhaja.</note> is the border. Beyond that are the border regions.”</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s Past Life</head>
                            <p n="1.181">The monks had doubts and asked the Blessed Buddha, who cuts all doubts, “Honorable One, what deed did the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa do that ripened into his being born in a rich, wealthy, prosperous family, with a jeweled earring attached to his ear, and, having seen the miserable realms, into his going forth in the Blessed One’s teachings, after which he abandoned all the afflictions and realized arhatship?”</p>
                            <p n="1.182">“Monks,” replied the Blessed One, “Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa himself performed the actions, and so forth, as above, up to…<note place="end">See <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Going Forth</hi> 4.306–4.307 for the full text of this formula.</note> are right, they alight upon embodied beings. Monks, in a time now passed, during this fortunate eon, when the lifespan of beings was twenty thousand years, the blessed Buddha Kāśyapa appeared in the world, a teacher, a one thus gone, an arhat, a perfectly awakened buddha, and so forth, up to…who knew the world.<note place="end">See <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Going Forth</hi> 4.306–4.307 for the full text of this formula.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.183">“In the town of Vārāṇasī lived a married couple, both of whom went for refuge and received the training precepts from the perfectly awakened Buddha Kāśyapa. When the perfectly awakened Buddha Kāśyapa had completed all the work of a buddha and passed beyond suffering into the expanse of nirvāṇa without remainder of aggregates, King Kṛkin had a stūpa built for him, made of four sorts of jewels. It was a league in circumference and half a league in height. The king gave the taxes collected at the gate on the eastern side of the city to that stūpa in order to make good any disrepair.</p>
                            <p n="1.184">“After King Kṛkin’s death, his son called Sujāta was put on the throne. His ministers rendered a tiny amount in tax revenue to him. He said to the ministers, ‘Why do you render a tiny amount in tax revenue to me? Are taxes not collected in my country?’</p>
                            <p n="1.185">“They replied, ‘Your Majesty, where can taxes be collected from? Your Majesty, those taxes that are collected from the gate on the eastern side of the city are to be used for making good any disrepair to your royal father’s stūpa. If Your Majesty approves, we will do away with that tax.’</p>
                            <p n="1.186">“He said, ‘Gentlemen, what was done by my father, that was done by Brahmā; that was done by Indra.’<note place="end">This statement seems to imply the divine right of kings, i.e. that a king rules with the imprimatur of the gods and thus a king’s wishes are inviolable. See Rotman 2008, p. 400, n. 201, for the difference between the text in the <hi rend="italic">Carmavastu</hi> and the <hi rend="italic">Divyāvadāna</hi>; the statement is in the negative in the latter.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.187">“They thought, ‘If His Majesty approves, we will ensure that those particular taxes are not collected.’ With this in mind, they arranged for the gate to be shut off and for the collection of taxes to stop from then on.</p>
                            <p n="1.188">“That stūpa fell into disrepair again, while the couple who had grown old continued to do the sweeping for the stūpa.</p>
                            <p n="1.189">“A merchant from the north took up his goods and, arriving in Vārāṇasī, saw that stūpa that had fallen into disrepair. On seeing it, he asked the couple, ‘Father, mother, this stūpa, whose is it?’ </p>
                            <p n="1.189">“They replied, ‘It is the perfectly awakened Buddha Kāśyapa’s.’</p>
                            <p n="1.190">“ ‘Who made it?’ </p>
                            <p n="1.190">“ ‘King Kṛkin.’</p>
                            <p n="1.191">“ ‘That King Kṛkin, did he not make a small donation for making good any disrepair to the stūpa?’ </p>
                            <p n="1.191">“The couple replied, ‘There was a donation, in that he gave the taxes collected from the eastern gate of the city to make good the stūpa when it fell into disrepair. After his death, his son named Sujāta was put on the throne. Because he did away with the collection of that tax, the stūpa fell into disrepair.’</p>
                            <p n="1.192">“The merchant took a jeweled earring from his ear and gave it to the couple, saying, ‘Father, mother, make good the disrepair to this stūpa with this precious earring. When I’ve traded my goods, I will come back and give you more.’</p>
                            <p n="1.193">“The couple sold the earring and, after repairing the dilapidated stūpa, they had something left over.</p>
                            <p n="1.194">“Some time later, after the merchant had traded his goods, he came back, bringing the profit. He saw that that stūpa wanted for nothing. Just looking at it, he rejoiced even more and gained faith, asking, ‘Father, mother, did you not incur some debt?’ </p>
                            <p n="1.194">“The couple replied, ‘Son, we haven’t incurred any debt at all; in fact, there is something left over.’</p>
                            <p n="1.195">“He gained great faith and gave what was left over and a further sum to the stūpa. Paying great homage to the stūpa with offerings, he made the aspiration, ‘By this virtuous root, may I be reborn into a rich, wealthy, prosperous family. May I attain a Dharma such as this. May I please just such a teacher, while not displeasing him.’</p>
                            <p n="1.196">“Monks, what do you think? That merchant was this very Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa. He who served the stūpa of the perfectly awakened Buddha Kāśyapa was born into a rich, wealthy, prosperous family, with a jeweled earring attached to his ear, through the ripening of that act of making an aspiration. He went forth in accordance with my teachings and, after abandoning all afflictions, he achieved arhatship. He has pleased me, a teacher who is equal in strength to the perfectly awakened Buddha Kāśyapa, equal in power, equal in diligence, possessing the quality that is equal to the unequaled, and he has not displeased me.</p>
                            <p n="1.197">“The ripened fruits of wholly negative actions are wholly negative, while the ripened fruits of wholly positive actions are wholly positive, and the ripened fruits of mixed actions are mixed. Monks, therefore abandon wholly negative and mixed actions and seek wholly positive actions. Monks, this is how you should train.”</p>
                            <p n="1.198">“Honorable One, what deed did the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa do that led to his seeing the miserable realms in this very lifetime?”</p>
                            <p n="1.199">The Blessed One said, “He spoke harshly to his mother. It is due to the ripening of that verbal act that he saw the miserable realms in this very lifetime.”</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="chapter">
                        <head type="chapter">Wide Beds</head>
                        <p n="1.200">The Blessed Buddha was staying in Śrāvastī, in Prince Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park. The venerable Upananda, who was new in the saṅgha, received, in accordance with his rank,<note place="end">Before every monsoon, a monastery’s monk residence caretaker assigns dwellings (Tib. <hi rend="italic">gnas khang</hi>) and bedding (Tib. <hi rend="italic">mal cha</hi>) to the monks in order of seniority (as determined by date of ordination), starting with the preceptors and instructors; see <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on the Rains Retreat</hi> (Toh 1-4), 1.17–1.26. Upananda is here described as “new,” that is, a new monk. In <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Going Forth</hi>, at the end of the ordination rite, monks are “enjoined to dwell in tranquility” with their monastic brothers. They are encouraged to respect the saṅgha’s hierarchy of seniority, which includes elders (Tib. <hi rend="italic">gnas brtan</hi>; Skt.<hi rend="italic"> sthavira</hi>), those who are middling (Tib. <hi rend="italic">bar ma</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">madhyama</hi>), and newcomers (Tib. <hi rend="italic">gsar bu</hi>). Dwellings and their furnishings are the subject of <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi>’s fifteenth chapter, <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Dwellings and Seating</hi>. For a study and translation of the first half of this chapter into English, see Schopen 2000.</note> a bed frame,<note place="end">Mattresses are to be placed on a “bed frame” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">khri</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">khaṭṭā</hi> or <hi rend="italic">maṃcaka</hi>). Here, in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>, “mattress” represents the Sanskrit terms <hi rend="italic">śayyā</hi> and <hi rend="italic">śayanāsana</hi>, which are rendered into Tibetan with <hi rend="italic">mal cha</hi>, <hi rend="italic">mal stan</hi>, <hi rend="italic">khri stan</hi>, <hi rend="italic">gnas mal che</hi>, <hi rend="italic">gdan</hi>, and <hi rend="italic">stan</hi>. In each case, the term refers to a cushioned seat or bed, i.e., a mattress. In the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya, the Sanskrit term <hi rend="italic">śayanāsana</hi> has several meanings, including (1) “mattress, bedding,” i.e., the soft parts of a bed; (2) “seating, furniture,” i.e., a couch installed in a monastery and used for either sleeping or sitting on in the hall; and (3) “dwelling, residence.” It has commonly been translated “bedding and seating,” though “dwelling and bedding” may be more apt.</note> which happened to be wobbly. Out of caution, he tried not to roll over as he slept. He thought, “I, Upananda, am attached even to couches. If I do not exchange the mattress or the bed frame, my name is not Upananda!”</p>
                        <p n="1.201">With this in mind, he got up early in the morning and presented himself to King Prasenajit of Kośala, who said to him, “Welcome, Honorable Upananda. Has the honorable Upananda slept well?”</p>
                        <p n="1.202">Upananda replied, “You pig!<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">gsus po che</hi> (Skt. <hi rend="italic">gillapeṭha</hi> and <hi rend="italic">gillapeṭṭa</hi>) is an epithet meaning “pot-bellied.” It is related to the Skt. Lambodara, an epithet of Gaṇeśa, which also carries the implication of “glutton.” Edgerton (BHSD, p. 212) says that here <hi rend="italic">gillapeṭṭa</hi> is used as a term of abuse. We have elected to translate it with “You pig!” This expression is certainly remarkable, and it is possible that Upananda was cloaking his insolence in faux respect with an expression akin to Your Rotundness. At 1.202, <hi rend="italic">gsus po che</hi> appears again in the Tibetan, this time appended with <hi rend="italic">ko sa la’i yul</hi>; see Tib. <hi rend="italic">gsus po che ko sa la’i yul rnams kho bo dbang ngam ci</hi>. The corresponding Sanskrit, however, does not include <hi rend="italic">gillapeṭha</hi>; see <hi rend="italic">kiṃ mama kosalo janapado vartate</hi>.</note> What do you think? How am I, Upananda, who is used to sleeping on an eight-layered mattress? As I am new in the saṅgha, I received, in accordance with my rank, a bed frame, which happens to be wobbly. Out of caution, I try not to roll over as I sleep.”</p>
                        <p n="1.203">“Honorable Upananda, an eight-layer mattress like this is suitable, it is highly suitable, it is superbly suitable. Where will it be prohibited? Who could prohibit it? If it is suitable, I give it to you. Take it and go on your way!”</p>
                        <p n="1.204">Upananda said, “You pig! Are the lands of Kośala my own? Have it delivered to the monastery and give it to me there!”</p>
                        <p n="1.205">Prasenajit gave him eight men. Four carried the mattress and four carried the bed frame. Brahmins and householders saw them walking in the middle of the road and upon seeing them, asked, “Gentlemen, where are you taking His Majesty’s bed today?” </p>
                        <p n="1.205">Upananda replied, “To its home.”</p>
                        <p n="1.206">“Why are you taking this bed?” </p>
                        <p n="1.206"> “These were obtained by me,” said Upananda.</p>
                        <p n="1.207">The brahmins and householders chastised, rebuked, and criticized him, saying, “Gentlemen, the ascetic Upananda is obsessed with sense pleasures, is he not?” </p>
                        <p n="1.207">So Upananda returned to his monastery dwelling, sprinkled water, swept, and spread a coat of fresh cow dung on the floor of the monastery dwelling. Then he arranged his mattress and was preparing to lie down when the Blessed One arrived.</p>
                        <p n="1.208">Upananda grew excited and said to him, “Honorable One, please look at the bed I have gotten!”<note place="end">Reading Stok Palace <hi rend="italic">bdag gi</hi>… in preference to Degé <hi rend="italic">bdag gis gnas mal ci ’dra ba mchis gzigs su gsol</hi>.</note></p>
                        <p n="1.209">Then the Blessed One said to the monks, “Monks, first of all, Upananda should be seen as a deluded person who conceals what is rotten.”<note place="end">“Deluded person who conceals what is rotten” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">rul pa sbed pa ni skyes bu gti mug</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">mohapuruṣaḥ prati­gopako</hi>). Edgerton (BHSD, p. 362, col. 1) glosses <hi rend="italic">pratigopaka</hi> as “concealer, one who acts secretly, on the sly.” There is nothing corresponding to <hi rend="italic">rul pa</hi> (“rotten”) in the Skt.</note></p>
                        <p n="1.210">The Blessed One then considered, “The problem that has arisen here is that the monks sleep on high beds and grand beds. That being the case, a monk should not sleep on a high bed or a grand bed. If he does so, he will be guilty of a breach.”</p>
                        <p n="1.211">After the Blessed One said that a monk should not sleep on a high bed or a grand bed, a householder invited the saṅgha of monks, the Buddha, and so on to his house and set about arranging high seats.<note place="end">“Seat” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">khri stan</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">āsana</hi>).</note></p>
                        <p n="1.212">The venerable Ānanda got there in advance and, when he saw him arranging the high seats, he said to him, “Householder, these seats are not appropriate for the monks, so gather them up.” The householder was starting to gather them up when the Blessed One arrived.</p>
                        <p n="1.213">Since the Blessed Buddha asks questions even though he knows the answers, the Blessed Buddha inquired of Ānanda, “Ānanda, what are you doing?”</p>
                        <p n="1.214">“Blessed One, after this householder had set out seats suitable for great men, I instructed him, ‘Householder, these seats are not appropriate for the monks, so gather them up!’ and now he’s gathering them up.”</p>
                        <p n="1.215">“Ānanda, know that such rules will not flourish everywhere, so, Ānanda, do not deter the householder from preparing the seats! That being the case, I allow that a monk may sit on a high seat in a house, but he may not lie on it. In a monastery, he may neither sit nor lie on high seat. If he sits or lies down on one, he will be guilty of a breach.”</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="chapter">
                        <head type="chapter">Calf</head>
                        <p n="1.216">A monk who observed the three-robe practice<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">dge slong chos gos gsum pa</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">traicīvarika</hi>. The original Vinaya rule established that all monks should own just three robes. Over time, monks were allowed to keep more, while limiting oneself to only three robes became one of a set of thirteen “practices of austerity” or <hi rend="italic">dhūtaguṇa</hi>. See Roach 2020, pp. 97–98.</note> came to Śrāvastī from the Southern Route<note place="end">In the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya, the “Southern Route” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">lho phyogs</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">dakṣiṇāpatha</hi>) refers to the Deccan region, centered on the capital city at Suvarṇagiri in modern-day Karnataka. See “Chapter IV: Dakkhiṇāpatha or The Deccan and the Far South” of Law’s <hi rend="italic">Geography of Early Buddhism</hi> (originally published in 1932, with an e-book edition prepared by Ānandajoti Bhikkhu in 2014). Later in this chapter, under summary 3, some of the Śākyans are said to have fled Virūḍhaka’s assault on Kapilavastu along the “Northern Route” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">nub phyogs</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">uttarāpatha</hi>). These two routes, the southern and northern, are old trade routes or trunk roads that led out of and into the Buddhist heartland.</note> in order to prostrate at the feet of the Blessed One. When Upananda saw the monk’s fine hide mat he said to him, “Alms seeker,<note place="end">“Alms seeker” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">bsod snyoms pa</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">piṇḍapātika</hi>). Upananda addresses the monk as a practitioner of another of the thirteen “practices of austerity,” namely, of relying only on alms (and not accepting invitations to meals offered by patrons). See Roach 2020, pp. 111–14.</note> give me that hide! I am going to pay homage at the feet of the Blessed One.”</p>
                        <p n="1.217">The monk replied, “Honorable Upananda, regardless of whether you go or not, I have come here to pay homage at the feet of the Blessed One.”</p>
                        <p n="1.218">“Alms seeker, what are you thinking? Do you think, ‘Upananda cannot get a hide like this’? Look at all I have gotten!”</p>
                        <p n="1.219">“Honorable Upananda, it is precisely because you can get one that I will not give you mine!”</p>
                        <p n="1.220">Upananda was acquainted with King Prasenajit of Kośala’s keeper of cattle, Vaḍra by name, so he went to see him, just at the time in the spring when beautiful, multicolored calves were born. Upananda rubbed the back of one of the calves, and Vaḍra said, “Honorable Upananda, do you want to drink the milk of this calf’s mother?”</p>
                        <p n="1.221">He replied, “I would like that too, but a monk who has a hide like this could devote himself to virtuous activities comfortably, with few concerns.” </p>
                        <p n="1.221">Vaḍra said, “Honorable Upananda, I understand what you have said.<note place="end">The Tibetan translation adds “what you have said” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">bka’ stsal pa</hi>) where the Sanskrit indicates only that it has “been understood” (Skt. <hi rend="italic">vijñātam</hi>).</note> Now go.”</p>
                        <p n="1.222">Upananda left, and Vaḍra instructed his cowherd, “Kill this calf, take the hide, and offer it to the honorable Upananda.”</p>
                        <p n="1.223">The cowherd killed the calf, took the hide, and set off. The mother cow followed him, lowing out of distress for her calf. When he entered Prince Jeta’s Grove, the cow stood at the gate of Prince Jeta’s Grove, lowing.</p>
                        <p n="1.224">Because blessed buddhas ask questions even though they know the answers, the Blessed Buddha inquired of the venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, why is this cow standing at the gate of Prince Jeta’s Grove, lowing?”</p>
                        <p n="1.225">The venerable Ānanda replied, “Blessed One, the honorable Upananda had the calf killed for its hide. That is why that cow is standing at the gate of Prince Jeta’s Grove, lowing.”</p>
                        <p n="1.226">The Blessed One said, “The problem that has arisen here is that the monks keep hides. That being the case, a monk may not keep a hide. If he does so, he will be guilty of a breach.”</p>
                        <p n="1.227">After the Blessed One said that a monk may not keep a hide, another householder invited the saṅgha of monks, the Buddha, and so on to a midday meal. As he did not have any other seating to set out, he began setting out seats made from hide.<note place="end">With the phrase “as before” (Skt. <hi rend="italic">pūrvavat</hi>), the Sanskrit (<hi rend="italic">pūrvavat tu na sarvatra saṃpatsyate</hi>) directs the reader to fill in the relevant material from the parallel passage in the preceding section. The Tibetan translation recites the passage in full, as represented in English translation.</note></p>
                        <p n="1.228">The venerable Ānanda got up early in the morning and went to the householder’s house. When he saw the householder setting out hide seats, he said, “Householder, since these seats are not appropriate for a monk, gather them up!”</p>
                        <p n="1.229">The householder was starting to gather the seats up when the Blessed One arrived there. Since blessed buddhas ask questions even though they know the answers, the Blessed Buddha inquired of the venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, what are you doing?”</p>
                        <p n="1.230">The venerable Ānanda replied, “As this householder does not have any other seating to set out, he set out these hide seats. I told him, ‘Householder, these seats are not appropriate for a monk, so gather them up!’ and now he’s gathering up these seats.”</p>
                        <p n="1.231">“Ānanda, know that such rules will not prosper everywhere, so, Ānanda, do not deter the householder from setting out the seats. In light of this, I allow that a monk may sit on a leather seat that has been set out in a house, but he may not lie down on it. In a monastery he may neither sit nor lie down on a leather seat. If he sits or lies down on one, he will be guilty of a breach.”</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="chapter">
                        <head type="chapter">Carriage, Swimming, Cow’s Tail and Inappropriate Motifs, and Wooden Sandals</head>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Carriage</head>
                            <p n="1.232">The Blessed Buddha was staying in the Bamboo Grove, the Kalandaka Sanctuary, near Rājagṛha.<note place="end">The following story is repeated, with some minor variation in details, in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Minor Matters of Monastic Discipline</hi>, vol. 10, F.106.a–107.a.</note> From the moment the venerable Pilindavatsa went forth, he was always ill.<note place="end">Venerable Pilindavatsa’s health ordeals are narrated in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Minor Matters of Monastic Discipline</hi>; see, e.g., F.104.b–106.b.</note> His friends came to see him, and when they got there he expounded the Dharma to them. After listening to the Dharma from the venerable Pilindavatsa, they went to their wives and said, “The noble Pilindavatsa has explained a Dharma like pressed honey, which is a delight to hear.”<note place="end">The Sanskrit for this section stops at the mention of the ever-ill Pilindavatsa and so does not contain the basis for the Tib. <hi rend="italic">sbrang rtsi btsir ba lta bu chos snyan dgu</hi> or “pressed honey-like Dharma that is a pleasure to hear.” While Yijing’s Chinese translation has him speak only a “Dharma that is sweet like pure honey” (Ch. <hi rend="italic">shuofa tianmei youru chun mi</hi> <hi rend="italic">説法甜美猶如淳蜜</hi>). We have translated the Tibetan <hi rend="italic">dgu</hi> as “delight.” It may also be taken as an indicator of plenty, as in the Tib. <hi rend="italic">yod dgu</hi>, “all that there is.” Finally, it may indicate how many (“nine”) Dharma topics were discussed, though this last seems unlikely here.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.233">Their wives said, “Your hearing the Dharma from the venerable one is the fruit of a buddha’s appearance. You would like to hear it again but we are embarrassed to go. If the noble one came to us here and expounded the Dharma, we too could listen.”</p>
                            <p n="1.234">The men said, “We will go to the noble Pilindavatsa and make the request.” They went to the venerable Pilindavatsa and, on arriving, said, “Noble Pilindavatsa, the women wish to hear the Dharma.” </p>
                            <p n="1.234">He replied, “Of course! Am I preventing them?”</p>
                            <p n="1.235">They said, “Noble one, the women are embarrassed to come to you. If the noble Pilindavatsa would go there and expound the Dharma, they would be able to listen.” </p>
                            <p n="1.235">He replied, “Gentlemen, I cannot go on foot because I am ill.”</p>
                            <p n="1.236">They said, “Noble one, travel by carriage!”<note place="end">“Carriage” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">bzhon pa</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">yāna</hi>).</note> </p>
                            <p n="1.236">“My friends, the Blessed One has not allowed that.”</p>
                            <p n="1.237">The monks reported this matter to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “That being the case, I allow that [a monk] may travel by carriage.”</p>
                            <p n="1.238">After the Blessed One said that a monk may travel by carriage, the venerable Pilindavatsa was riding in a carriage, surrounded by his wards and apprentices, when the group of six monks saw him and asked, “Gentlemen, who is that traveler over there?” </p>
                            <p n="1.238">The wards and apprentices replied, “It is our preceptor.”</p>
                            <p n="1.239">“Has the Blessed One allowed a carriage?” </p>
                            <p n="1.239">“He has.”</p>
                            <p n="1.240">The group of six monks said, “The Blessed One thinks the Śākyans are so soft that they cannot travel by foot, and so the Blessed One has allowed a carriage.” With this in mind, they prepared carriages of gold and silver and lapis lazuli and variegated crystal, polished like a lotus. While riding in such a carriage in the center of the road, they stuck out their arms and hailed, “Be well!” to brahmins and householders.</p>
                            <p n="1.241">The brahmins and householders asked, “Noble ones, has the Blessed One allowed these carriages?” </p>
                            <p n="1.241">“He has.” </p>
                            <p n="1.241">They said, “Noble ones, you ascetics are obsessed with sense pleasures.”</p>
                            <p n="1.242">Other monks reported what they said to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One reflected, “The problem that has arisen here is that the monks travel by carriage. That being the case, a monk should not travel by carriage.”</p>
                            <p n="1.243">When that in turn became a problem, the Blessed One said, “There are two situations in which a monk may travel by carriage: when he is weak and infirm from old age, and when he is ill and unable to tolerate exertion.”</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Swimming</head>
                            <p n="1.244">Some monks left to wander the countryside. Carrying their robes and begging bowls, they crossed a river, getting as far as the middle until they could go no farther. Monks reported this incident to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “That being the case, I allow that a monk may learn how to swim.”</p>
                            <p n="1.245">After the Blessed One had said that a monk may learn how to swim, the group of six monks swam to and fro across the great river Ajiravatī. When some female cowherds arrived, the group of six saw them and said, “Sisters, come here! We will save you!”</p>
                            <p n="1.246">In the process of saving them, the group of six touched their hands and arms and after saving them, they said, “Sisters, come back here! We’ll save you again!”</p>
                            <p n="1.247">The women chastised, rebuked, and criticized them, saying, “Noble ones, since you have touched our hands and arms in a way that not even our husbands touch us, why should we come back?”</p>
                            <p n="1.248">Monks reported this matter to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said,<note place="end">“Said,” following the Sanskrit (<hi rend="italic">bhagavān āha</hi>) rather than the Tibetan <hi rend="italic">bcom ldan ’das kyis dgongs pa</hi> or “the Blessed One reflected.” In the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya, the Buddha is often described as first reflecting on a situation and then announcing a new rule to address the situation.</note> “The problem that has arisen here is that the monks have been touching women. That being the case, a monk may not touch a woman. If he does so, he will be guilty of a breach.”</p>
                            <p n="1.249">After the Blessed One said that a monk may not touch a woman, city folk who enjoyed gardens visited a garden. One of the women went down into the river, slipped, and was carried off by the water. Her husband, who went in search of her, saw the monks and asked, “Noble ones, have you seen my wife who has been carried off by the water?” </p>
                            <p n="1.249">“We saw her. The water has carried her over there.”</p>
                            <p n="1.250">“Have you been standing here all day looking at the water while she’s almost drowning over there?” </p>
                            <p n="1.250">Monks reported this incident to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “She should be removed. Others may say, ‘Let me go!’ If they are able to swim, they should be released.”</p>
                            <p n="1.251">The monks covered the other women, who lay motionless and face down, under mounds of sand and left, but then the corpses were eaten by jackals. </p>
                            <p n="1.251">“A monk should not leave without disposing of a female corpse.”</p>
                            <p n="1.252">When the monks grew desirous while disposing of female corpses, the Blessed One said, “Sit down elsewhere, and those who recite should recite while those who meditate should direct their attention. If a monk becomes worried about lunch, he should entrust the female corpses to a cowherd or shepherd in the vicinity and then depart.”</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Cow’s Tail and Inappropriate Motifs</head>
                            <p n="1.253">The group of six monks grabbed the tail of a householder’s cow and swam to and fro [in the river] until the cow ran out of milk.</p>
                            <p n="1.254">The householder asked the cowherd, “Why is there no milk today?” </p>
                            <p n="1.254">He replied, “The noble ones, the group of six monks…,” etc., as above, up to chastised, rebuked, and criticized them.</p>
                            <p n="1.255">The Blessed One said, “That being the case, a monk may not swim while holding on to a cow’s tail.”</p>
                            <p n="1.256">After the Blessed One said that a monk may not swim while holding on to a cow’s tail, some monks were crossing a river holding on to an elephant’s tail when they decided they did not want to cross. The Blessed One said, “A monk may hold the tails of any of five types of animals with tails when crossing: a well-bred elephant, a well-bred horse, a prize bull, a buffalo, or a yak. However, a monk should swim with a bladder.”<note place="end">“Bladder” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">rkyal pa</hi>). In his edition of the Sanskrit manuscripts from Gilgit, Dutt (1950) reads Skt. <hi rend="italic">bhṛṣi</hi>. See though Bhattacarya’s discussion of the Vedic <hi rend="italic">dṛti</hi> or “leather container” and its later meanings of “inflated skin bag” or “bladder and bellows.” Thanks to Shayne Clarke for this reference.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.257">After the Blessed One said that a bladder should be used when swimming, the group of six monks made bladders, polished like a lotus, with colorful motifs depicting women and men making love. Brahmins and householders saw them and said, “Noble ones, what is this?” </p>
                            <p n="1.257">They replied, “The Blessed One has allowed a bladder.” </p>
                            <p n="1.257">“Noble ones, you ascetics are obsessed with sense pleasures.”</p>
                            <p n="1.258">Monks reported these disparaging words to the Blessed One‍—and the Blessed One said, “An ascetic may not keep bladders, polished like a lotus, with colorful motifs depicting women and men making love. He may, however, keep one of two types of bladder: one for dye<note place="end">“Dye” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">rtsis bskus pa</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">kāṣāya</hi>); that is, dye used to dye cloth when it is to be made into robes.</note> and one to be used as a rudder.”<note place="end">“Rudder” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">rkyal skya</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">tāraṇika</hi>).</note></p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Wooden Sandals</head>
                            <p n="1.259">The householder Anāthapiṇḍada built a garden. When monks wearing wooden sandals arrived to listen to the Dharma, their wooden sandals scraped the polished floor and ruined it.</p>
                            <p n="1.260">The householder Anāthapiṇḍada, who had gotten up early to go and bow at the feet of the Blessed One, saw what had happened and asked the monks, “Noble ones, oh my, did King Prasenajit, together with the four branches of the army, set up camp for the night here?” </p>
                            <p n="1.260">“It was not the king,” they replied, “but some monks who arrived wearing wooden sandals. They spoiled this.”</p>
                            <p n="1.261">Monks reported their disparaging words to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One reflected, “The problem that has arisen here is that the monks wear wooden sandals. That being the case, a monk may not wear wooden sandals.”</p>
                            <p n="1.262">After the Blessed One said that a monk may not wear wooden sandals, some monks pledged to spend the rains retreat in an apartment. When their sandals got wet with mud, monks reported this incident to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “A monk may keep wooden sandals to wear inside an apartment.”</p>
                            <p n="1.263">When faithful brahmins and householders offered wooden sandals to the saṅgha of monks, the monks did not accept them.</p>
                            <p n="1.264">The brahmins and householders said, “Nobles ones, until the Blessed Buddha appeared in the world, we were patrons of the tīrthikas…” and so forth, up to “Accept [the gifts].”<note place="end">The text refers to a formula found in full in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Minor Matters of Monastic Discipline</hi>, which reads, “Noble ones, until the Blessed Buddha appeared in the world, we were patrons of the tīrthikas. Now that the Blessed Buddha has appeared in the world, we are your patrons. If you do not accept [our gifts], you leave us without provisions on the path of virtue from this life to the next, do you not? Accept [the gifts].” See Toh 6, F.205.b: <hi rend="italic">’phags pa dag gang gi tshe sangs rgyas bcom ldan ’das ’jig rten du ma byung ba de’i tshe ni mu stegs can rnams sbyin gnas lags/bcom ldan ’das ’jig rten du byung na da ltar khyed sbyin gnas lags na/ gal te khyed mi bzhes na ci bdag cag ’jig rten ’di nas ’jig rten pha rol tu dge ba’i lam rgyags ma mchis par mchi’am</hi>.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.265">The Blessed One said, “[Wooden sandals] should be accepted and placed in the saṅgha’s toilet or privy.”<note place="end">The “toilet” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">snam phyi sa</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">varcaskuṭi</hi>) is for defecating, while the “privy” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">chab khung</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">prasrāvakuṭi</hi>) is for urination.</note> [B22]</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Summary 2</head>
                    <p n="1.266">A summary:</p>
                    <lg n="1.267">
                        <l><hi rend="italic">Bamboo leaves; Śroṇa; Allow to protect; Likewise, lace up crosswise; Toe cover, and heel cover.</hi></l>
                    </lg>
                    <div type="chapter">
                        <head type="chapter">Bamboo Leaves</head>
                        <p n="1.268">After the Blessed One said that a monk may not keep wooden sandals, they wore bamboo-leaf sandals.<note place="end">The content of the text continues from the previous section despite the summary break. This may explain the absence of a <hi rend="italic">nidāna</hi> or narrative “setting,” which ordinarily comes immediately after an <hi rend="italic">uddāna</hi> or “summary” in <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi> and <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Minor Matters of Monastic Discipline</hi>.</note> When that in turn became a problem, the Blessed One said, “Bamboo-leaf sandals may not be worn.”</p>
                        <p n="1.269">When the monks wore muñja grass sandals and that in turn became a problem, the Blessed One said, “Muñja grass sandals may not be worn.”</p>
                        <p n="1.270">When they wore rope sandals and that in turn became a problem, the Blessed One said, “Rope sandals may not be worn.”</p>
                        <p n="1.271">When the monks developed rheumatism<note place="end">Here, our identification of Skt. <hi rend="italic">vātaśonita</hi> (Tib. <hi rend="italic">dreg gyis btab pa</hi>) with “rheumatism” is based on Sanskrit and Tibetan dictionaries. The “abscesses” (<hi rend="italic">shu ba</hi>) mentioned in the Tibetan translation could correspond to tophi, masses of uric acid crystals that burst open under pressure, which develop in people with tophaceous gout, a type of rheumatism. Gout, however, is a condition associated with overnutrition and so is unlikely to have been widespread in ancient India.</note> because their leather sandals remained wet when they were inundated.<note place="end">Yijing’s Chinese translation states that monks developed an illness or pain in their hips, which caused them so much pain that they would always have to sprinkle water, which left their leather sandals wet; see Yijing’s Taishō 1447, 1055c10–11: <hi rend="italic">liang bi you bing kutong suo bi dang yi shuilin pi lu zong lan</hi> <hi rend="italic">兩髀有病苦痛所逼當以水淋皮履總爛</hi>.</note> Monks reported the matter to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “A monk who develops rheumatism may wear rope sandals.”</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="chapter">
                        <head type="chapter">Śroṇa</head>
                        <p n="1.272">When Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa went forth, he had gold-colored hairs four finger-widths long on the soles of his feet. On seeing this, the group of six said, “Nanda, Upananda! How will this ball of fresh butter make single-pointed effort now that he has gone forth in the Teaching?”</p>
                        <p n="1.273">On hearing what they said, Śroṇa’s pride was piqued. He went to the venerable Ānanda and asked him, “Honorable Ānanda, how, in the Blessed One’s telling, does a person with single-pointed effort remain in absorption on the Teaching?” </p>
                        <p n="1.273">“Venerable Śroṇa, it is attained by walking.”<note place="end">Here, the phrase “by walking” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">’chag pas</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">caṃkramya</hi>) refers to walking meditation, as mentioned in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on the Restoration Rite</hi> at 1.57, where the Buddha advises monks who feel sleepy while doing seated meditation to do walk a bit to dispel the torpor.</note></p>
                        <p n="1.274">Śroṇa went to the Śitavana cemetery, where he practiced walking,<note place="end">“Practiced walking” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">’chags bcas so</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">caṃkrame ’dhiṣṭhitaḥ</hi>).</note> and the walking wore down the gold-colored hairs, which had been four finger-widths long. Moreover, his skin cracked and then started to bleed. As he went from one end of the walkway to the other, crows drank his blood at both ends.</p>
                        <p n="1.275">It is natural that blessed buddhas who live and remain in the world need, from time to time, to swim in order to cross a river, and so forth.<note place="end">The Skt. and Tib. texts direct the reader to fill in material, though in this case it is not obvious where in <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi> the full citation can be found. Nor is it obvious why the text refers to crossing a river, which is taken up under the heading “Swimming,” below: Tib. <hi rend="italic">chos nyid kyis sangs rgyas bcom ldan ’das rnams bzhugs shing ’tsho la gzhes pa ni dus dus su chu bor rgyu ba spyod do // zhes bya ba’i bar du rgyas par bya ste / skabs ’dir ni</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">dharmatā khalu buddhā bhagavanto jīvantas tiṣṭhanto dhriyamāṇā yāpayantaḥ kālena kālaṃ nadīcārikāṃ caranti vistareṇa yāvad evāsmiṃs tv arthe</hi>.</note> On this occasion, the Blessed Buddha came to the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa’s monastery and saw his walkway. Because blessed buddhas ask questions even though they know the answers, upon seeing him, the Blessed Buddha, although he knew, inquired of the venerable Ānanda, “Ānanda, which monk does this walkway for one-pointed effort belong to?” </p>
                        <p n="1.275">“It is Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa’s.”</p>
                        <p n="1.276">“Ānanda, that being the case, I allow that Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa may affix a single lining to his sandals, but not a second layer, nor a third layer. If it breaks down, it can be patched and kept.”</p>
                        <p n="1.277">The venerable Ānanda then went to the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa and said to the venerable Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa, “Venerable one, you should know: The Teacher has allowed you to affix a single lining in your sandals, but not a second layer, nor a third layer…and so forth, as before.”</p>
                        <p n="1.278">“Honorable Ānanda, is this allowance for the whole saṅgha, or only for me?” </p>
                        <p n="1.278">“Only for you.”</p>
                        <p n="1.279">“Honorable Ānanda, the Teacher’s command is not to be disregarded. However, if I were to keep them, it would give my fellow brahmacārins grounds to say to me, ‘Ah, Śrona Koṭiviṃśa has received a privileged position since going forth. Look at how the one who abandoned the unique country of Campā with its host of seven elephants and went forth, now clings to sandals with a single lining!’ Be that as it may, if the Blessed One would concur with me and make the allowance for the whole saṅgha, I would keep them as well.”</p>
                        <p n="1.280">The venerable Ānanda reported Śroṇa’s words to the Blessed One at length, and the Blessed One said, “That being the case, thanks to Śroṇa Koṭiviṃśa, I allow that the whole saṅgha may keep sandals with a single lining affixed, but not a second layer, nor a third layer…and so forth, as before.”</p>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Allow to Protect</head>
                            <p n="1.281">A latecomer monk<note place="end">“Latecomer” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">rgan zhugs</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">mahalla</hi> and <hi rend="italic">mahallaka</hi>). “Latecomer” refers to those who join the saṅgha late in life, generally in retirement from a household life. See Śīlapālita (Toh 4115, F.43.b): <hi rend="italic">rgan zhugs zhes bya ba ni na tshod rgas nas rab tu byung ba’o</hi>. It is not a technical term for a monastic station in the way novice, monk, and nun are, as they each require a profession. There is no Chinese translation for this portion of the present text, but in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Going Forth</hi> (Taishō 1444), Yijing translates the term <hi rend="italic">you nian lao</hi> <hi rend="italic">有年老</hi>.</note> walked in front of the Blessed One while wearing sandals. The Blessed One said to that monk, “Monk, go away. Do not stand in front of me.”</p>
                            <p n="1.282">Then the Blessed One said to the monks, “Monks, if the disciples of a teacher who is entangled in all of the world’s luxuries do not swiftly and easily resort to ways of life leading to downfall, how much more so those of one who is detached from all of the world’s luxuries?”<note place="end">Here, the Buddha allows that a teacher preoccupied with wealth may have students who do not emulate his avarice and therefore may avoid the pitfalls that the teacher falls into, i.e., the miserable realms of existence. But, since it will be all the easier for the students of a teacher who exhibits restraint toward wealth and material goods to avoid those pitfalls, the Buddha goes on to ban the keeping of lined sandals.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.283">The Blessed One considered, “The problem that has arisen here is that the monks wear sandals. That being the case, a monk may not wear sandals.”</p>
                            <p n="1.284">After the Blessed One said that a monk may not wear sandals, a dancer who had gone forth had a broken water jug. So, after he had washed his feet at the foot-washing building, he filled up the jug with water and walked away in the peacock’s gait.<note place="end">The “peacock’s gait” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">rma bya’i ’gros</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">mayūragati</hi>) is the name of a meter but the Skt. <hi rend="italic">gati</hi> also means “gait, (dance) step.” Here, the monks presumably adopts this gait so as not to spill the water he is carrying.</note> The group of six monks saw him and said, “Venerable ones, the monk dances without musical accompaniment. Let us play him some music!” and they began to make music with their mouths.</p>
                            <p n="1.285">The other monks asked them, “Why are you being so frivolous?”<note place="end">The translation here follows the Sanskrit (<hi rend="italic">kim auddhatyam kuruta</hi>). The Tibetan <hi rend="italic">ci ma grangs pa byed dam</hi> may be rendered as, “Are you acting without account?”</note> </p>
                            <p n="1.285">They replied, “What is frivolous about this? Have you not seen that monk dancing without music?”</p>
                            <p n="1.286">Monks reported this incident to the Blessed One. Because blessed ones ask questions even though they know the answers, the Buddha, although he knew the answer, asked that monk, “Monk, what was your intention in acting like that?” </p>
                            <p n="1.286">“Honorable One, I was acting to protect the dwellings.”</p>
                            <p n="1.287">“Since this monk was acting to protect the dwellings, he has incurred no offense. That being the case, I allow that sandals with a single lining may be worn to protect the dwellings, but not a second lining, nor a third. If it breaks down, it can be patched and kept.”</p>
                            <p n="1.288">After the Blessed One said that sandals with a single lining may be worn, a householder became devoted to an alms seeker.<note place="end">That is, a monk who relies only on alms and does not accept invitations to meals offered by patrons. Living only by alms is one of the thirteen “practices of austerity,” on which see Roach 2020, pp. 111–14.</note> The latter got up early and entered Śrāvastī on his alms round, without any sandals. The householder saw him without sandals and said, “Does the noble one not have sandals? Come! Let us go to see the shoemaker, and I will see that he gives you sandals.”</p>
                            <p n="1.289">He went to the shoemaker and said to him, “Ah, my good man! Give a pair of sandals to the noble one here.” After giving his instructions, he left.</p>
                            <p n="1.290">At that time, sandals with single linings were made in two cases: for monks and for the dead. Although that monk went to see the shoemaker time and time again, he did not give him the sandals.</p>
                            <p n="1.291">Later, the householder saw the monk again without any sandals, and on seeing him he said, “Noble one, did the shoemaker not give you sandals?” </p>
                            <p n="1.291">“Householder, have you not heard that telling the truth is a rarity in a shoemaker? I went again and again, but he did not give them to me.”</p>
                            <p n="1.292">“Noble one, come! Let us go to my house,” replied the householder. </p>
                            <p n="1.292">He took the monk home and, after the monk had his fill of nourishing food, the householder gave him a pair of sandals with many linings. </p>
                            <p n="1.292">The monk said, “Householder, the Blessed One has not allowed these.”<note place="end">Here and in the following five instances of this phrase, the Tibetan translation of <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi> translates the Skt. prefix <hi rend="italic">anu-</hi> with the Tib. prefix <hi rend="italic">rjes su</hi> (Skt. <hi rend="italic">bhagavata nānujñātam</hi>; Tib. <hi rend="italic">bcom ldan ’das kyis rjes su ma gnang ngo</hi>). In <hi rend="italic">The Chapters on Monastic Discipline</hi> and the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya more broadly, this formula is more commonly seen in Tibetan without the prefix (e.g., Tib. <hi rend="italic">bcom ldan ’das kyis ma gnang ngo</hi>). <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Going Forth</hi> (Toh 1-1, 1.659) distinguishes between a “prescription” (Skt. <hi rend="italic">prajñapti</hi>; Tib. <hi rend="italic">bcas pa</hi>) and a “supplementary prescription” (Skt. <hi rend="italic">anuprajñapti</hi>; Tib. <hi rend="italic">rjes su bcas pa</hi>). Here in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>, however, the Sanskrit prefix <hi rend="italic">anu</hi>- does not appear to carry any additional semantic value.</note></p>
                            <p n="1.293">He replied, “Noble one, take them. Go and make them into sandals with a single lining; then you may wear them.”</p>
                            <p n="1.294">The monk took them and returned to the monastery. Taking the sandals and a knife, he sat down at the foot of a tree, where he started to take them apart.</p>
                            <p n="1.295">The Blessed One came by that place and asked, “Monk, what are you doing?” </p>
                            <p n="1.295">“After the Blessed One banned sandals with many linings, I got these ones with multiple linings. I’ll make them into single-lined sandals and wear them.”</p>
                            <p n="1.296">Then the Blessed One reflected, “Oh dear, see how devoted brahmins and householders give sandals with many linings to my disciples! That being the case, I allow that monks may wear sandals with many linings if the sandals were used by a householder.”</p>
                            <p n="1.297">The venerable Upāli asked, and so forth, up to,<note place="end">It is unclear what text these instructions intend to be supplied here. No further content is necessary for coherence.</note> “Honorable One, the Blessed One has said that monks may wear sandals with many linings if the sandals were used by a householder. Honorable One, how should one interpret ‘used by a householder’?”</p>
                            <p n="1.298">“Upāli, if they have been worn for at least seven or eight paces, they meet the requirement.”</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="chapter">
                        <head type="chapter">Lace up Crosswise, Toe Cover, and Heel Cover</head>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">The Noble Ones Steal Sandals</head>
                            <p n="1.299">The setting was at Vaiśālī.<note place="end">Vaiśālī was the capital of the Vṛji/Vaji/Vajji (Tib. <hi rend="italic">spong byed</hi>; Pali <hi rend="italic">Vajji</hi>) republic, home to the Malla and Licchavi people and one of the sixteen <hi rend="italic">mahājanapada</hi> of ancient India (Edgerton <hi rend="italic">vaji</hi>, p. 467, col. 1). The Vaji Republic was Magadha’s immediate neighbor to the north and northeast, their territory including a swath of the Himālayan foothills. The <hi rend="italic">mahājanapada</hi> of Aśmaka, by contrast, where Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa’s story takes place, was to the far south of Magadha, around the Godāvarī River in modern-day Maharasthra.</note> At that time they made the following sorts of sandals in Vaiśālī: creaking sandals,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">thrig thrig</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">hinihināyamānā</hi>, which BHSD, p. 620, suggests is onomatopoeic.</note> tinkling sandals,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">tshig tshig</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">kiṇikiṇāyamānā</hi>, which BHSD, p. 183, suggests is onomatopoetic.</note> sparkling sandals,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">chem chem</hi>; no equivalent in Skt. Or this might also be onomatopoeic, reflecting a loud sound; see WTS, pp. 271–72.</note> ram’s horn sandals,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">lug ru</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">meṇḍaviṣāṇikā</hi>.</note> sandals like a bodhi leaf,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">byang chub kyi shing gi lo ma lta bu</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">bodhi­paṭapatrakā</hi>.</note> multicolored sandals,<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">khra bo</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">citropacitrā</hi>.</note> and sandals that cost five coins. The group of six monks saw someone wearing some sandals, and they pressed down on the heel of his sandals with their big toes and pushed him by the nape of his neck. Saying, “By your giving this donation, may you attain mental adornment,<note place="end">Although the group of six constantly flout Buddhist doctrine, they are well versed in it and frequently quote it for their own ends. The four attainments they list here flow from practicing “relinquishment,” i.e., donating possessions to others. For a systematic presentation of “relinquishment” and the other “requisites” on the spiritual path of the śrāvaka, see the <hi rend="italic">Śrāvakabhūmi</hi>, summarized and discussed by Kragh 2013, pp. 110–18.</note> the mental requirements, the requisites for practicing yoga, and the ultimate goal‍—buddhahood!” they took the sandals. News spread everywhere: “The noble ones steal shoes like that.”</p>
                            <p n="1.300">They stole such sandals from an older noblewoman. The son-in-law came to her, and after giving her a pair of sandals, instructed her, “Since the noble ones steal sandals, be alert, and by all means, do not allow them to steal these!”</p>
                            <p n="1.301">Some time later, the son-in-law saw an alms seeker entering Vaiśālī on his alms round. The man went into a house, and the monk entered it too. The man left the house and entered another house. The monk then entered that one too. The man said, “Noble one, why are you following in my footsteps, unless perhaps you wish to steal these sandals?”</p>
                            <p n="1.302">“My friend, I will not steal your sandals; rather, I have come here for alms.” </p>
                            <p n="1.302">The man said, “Noble one, whether you steal them or not, everywhere it is said that you noble ones steal sandals.”</p>
                            <p n="1.303">Monks reported what people were saying to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One reflected, “The problem that has arisen here is that the monks wear creaking sandals, and so forth in full from above.<note place="end">The full text above (1.294) reads “creaking sandals, tinkling sandals, sparkling sandals, ram’s horn sandals, sandals like a bodhi leaf, multicolored sandals, and sandals that cost five coins.”</note> A monk should not wear such sandals. If a monk wears such sandals, he will be guilty of a breach.”</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                    <div type="chapter">
                        <head type="chapter">Lace Up Crosswise</head>
                        <p n="1.304">The setting was at Śrāvastī. At that time, when brahmins and householders saw that the monks’ sandals caused sores on the tops of their feet, they said, “It is your sandals that are causing sores on the tops of your feet. Why do you not wear sandals that lace up crosswise?” </p>
                        <p n="1.304">“The Blessed One has not allowed them.”</p>
                        <p n="1.305">Monks reported this incident to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “That being the case, I allow that sandals laced up crosswise may be worn.”</p>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Toe Cover</head>
                            <p n="1.306">Monks developed sores on their big toes while climbing Vulture Peak Mountain. Brahmins and householders saw them and said, “You developed sores on your big toes from climbing Vulture Peak Mountain. Why do you not wear sandals with toe covers?”<note place="end">The translation “with toe cover” follows the Skt. <hi rend="italic">puṭāpuṭī</hi>, which suggests a small piece of cloth, in preference to the Tibetan (<hi rend="italic">rtse mo sbu bu can</hi>), which seems to read “with a hole at the toe.”</note> </p>
                            <p n="1.306">“The Blessed One has not allowed them.”</p>
                            <p n="1.307">Monks reported this incident to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “That being the case, I allow that a monk may wear sandals with toe covers.”</p>
                        </div>
                        <div type="section">
                            <head type="section">Heel Cover</head>
                            <p n="1.308">When brahmins and householders saw that monks developed sores on their heels when coming down from Vulture Peak Mountain, they asked, “Noble ones, how did you develop sores on your heels?” </p>
                            <p n="1.308">“Coming down from Vulture Peak Mountain.”</p>
                            <p n="1.309">“Why do you not wear sandals with heel covers?” </p>
                            <p n="1.309">“The Blessed One has not allowed them.”</p>
                            <p n="1.310">Monks reported this incident to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “That being the case, I allow that a monk may wear sandals with heel covers.”</p>
                        </div>
                    </div>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Summary 3</head>
                    <p n="1.311">A summary:</p>
                    <lg n="1.312">
                        <l>Ankle boots and boots; Buskins in snowy regions; Allowing bearskin; Awls, straps, and knives.</l>
                    </lg>
                    <div type="chapter">
                        <head type="chapter">Ankle Boots and Boots</head>
                        <p n="1.313">The setting was at Śrāvastī. When brahmins and householders saw that the new grass cut the monks’ feet, they asked, “Noble ones, what has caused the cuts on your feet?” </p>
                        <p n="1.313">“New grass.”</p>
                        <p n="1.314">“Why did not you wear ankle boots?”<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">lham mgul chad</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">nālāmbujā</hi>. The Tibetan suggests a boot, i.e., in which the “neck” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">mgul</hi>) has been “cut” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">chad</hi>). The Skt. literally means “hollow stalked lotus,” apparently in reference to the hollow bootleg.</note> </p>
                        <p n="1.314">“The Blessed One has not allowed them.”</p>
                        <p n="1.315">Monks reported this incident to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “That being the case, I allow that ankle boots may be worn.”</p>
                        <p n="1.316">When the new grass grew tall, the monks’ legs were cut even worse.<note place="end">The following few lines are not found in the Skt. MSS.</note> On seeing this, brahmins and householders asked, “How did your legs get cut even worse?” </p>
                        <p n="1.316">They replied, “When the new grass grew tall, it cut our legs even worse.”</p>
                        <p n="1.317">“Noble ones, why did not you wear boots?”<note place="end">Tib. <hi rend="italic">lham yu’u thung</hi>, or <hi rend="italic">lham yu thung</hi>, lit. “short boot”; Skt. <hi rend="italic">muṇḍapūlā</hi>.</note> </p>
                        <p n="1.317">“The Blessed One has not allowed them.”</p>
                        <p n="1.318">Monks reported this incident to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “That being the case, I allow that boots may be worn.”</p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="chapter">
                        <head type="chapter">Buskins in Snowy Regions</head>
                        <p n="1.320">As the deluded Virūḍhaka was killing the Śākyans of Kapilavastu,<note place="end">For much of the Buddha’s teaching career, Virūḍhaka ruled Kośala, the <hi rend="italic">mahājanapada</hi> that neighbored the Śākyan homeland of Kapilavastu, and its capital at Śrāvastī. Virūḍhaka was the son of King Prasenajit and a Śākyan maidservant. He is said to have nursed a lifelong grievance against the Śākyans and, after his father’s death, launched a savage attack on them, as described here. See <hi rend="italic">The Princeton Dictionary of Buddhism</hi> (2014, p. 980).</note> some of them fled west to the Northern Route,<note place="end">The Tib. reads <hi rend="italic">nub phyogs</hi> or “west” while the Skt. reads <hi rend="italic">uttarāpatha</hi> or “Northern Route.” The lands that made up the Northern Route lay due west of Kapilavastu, just north of the Nepal border, which perhaps explains the discrepancy between the Skt. and Tib., which we have combined in our translation.</note> while some went as far as Nepal.<note place="end">“Nepal”: Tib. <hi rend="italic">bal yul</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">naivāla</hi> (i.e. Naipāla).</note></p>
                        <p n="1.321">Merchants from Śrāvastī brought their wares and came to Nepal. When the Śākyans saw them, they said, “Gentlemen, from where have you come today?”<note place="end">This portion is not found in the Sanskrit.</note> </p>
                        <p n="1.321">The merchants replied, “From Śrāvastī.”</p>
                        <p n="1.322">“If our beloved kin, the noble Ānanda, is there, would you give the noble Ānanda the message that, upon coming here, you spoke with us?” </p>
                        <p n="1.322">The merchants said, “We<note place="end">Reading with Stok Palace <hi rend="italic">bdag gis</hi> in preference to Degé <hi rend="italic">bdag gi</hi>.</note> will go to the noble Ānanda and deliver the message.”</p>
                        <p n="1.323">Taking goods to be traded, they arrived in Śrāvastī and said to the noble Ānanda, “Noble Ānanda, your beloved kin are in Nepal, and they wish to see you.”</p>
                        <p n="1.324">The venerable Ānanda, who had not seen his beloved kin,<note place="end">The translation combines the Tibetan <hi rend="italic">gnyen la gdung ba yin pas</hi> or “who longed for his kin” with the Skt. <hi rend="italic">āryānando jñātivatsalo nāsmākam avalokayatīti / yāvat tais tasyārocitam</hi>.</note> went to Nepal to see them. His hands and feet cracked from the cold, and the monks said to him, “Venerable Ānanda, why do your hands and feet look like torn lotus leaves?” </p>
                        <p n="1.324">“On account of the cold,” he replied.</p>
                        <p n="1.325">“Since your kin wear buskins,<note place="end">“Buskins” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">lham sgro gu can</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">pūlā</hi> or <hi rend="italic">maṇḍapūlā</hi>). A buskin is a calf- or knee-high boot.</note> why do you not wear them?” </p>
                        <p n="1.325">“The Blessed One has not allowed them.”</p>
                        <p n="1.326">Other monks reported this incident to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “That being the case, I allow that buskins may be worn in snowy regions.”</p>
                        <p n="1.327">The venerable Upāli asked the Blessed Buddha, “Honorable One, the Blessed One has said that buskins may be worn in snowy regions. Honorable One, what is a ‘snowy region’?” </p>
                        <p n="1.327">“Upāli, it is a place where water freezes in the jug.”</p>
                        <p n="1.328">A hunter became devoted to a monk and offered him a bearskin that he had obtained, but the monk did not accept it. The hunter followed the monk and said, “Noble one, I am offering you a bearskin that I have obtained, so please accept it!” That monk still did not accept it.</p>
                        <p n="1.329">The Blessed One then too came to that place. Since blessed buddhas ask questions even though they know the answers, asking although he knew the answer, the Blessed Buddha inquired of Ānanda, “Ānanda, why is that hunter over there following this monk?”</p>
                        <p n="1.330">“Honorable One, when that hunter obtained a bearskin he presented it to this monk, but the monk did not accept it, so the hunter came here following this monk.”</p>
                        <p n="1.331">The Blessed One said, “Ānanda, a hunter with faith is a rarity. If he comes across a hundred or a thousand beings, he kills them. So therefore, if a hunter gives a bearskin, it may be accepted. Having been accepted, it should be spread out at the door of the perfumed chamber<note place="end">The “perfumed chamber” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">dri gtsang khang</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">gandhakuṭi</hi>) is a shrine room, generally containing a statue or painting of the Buddha, and therefore a place that lay people might visit when paying homage at the monastery. For more, see Schopen 2015.</note> or underfoot, where it may benefit the eye.”<note place="end">“Benefit the eye” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">mig la phan no</hi>; Skt. <hi rend="italic">cākṣuṣyaṃ svasti</hi>). Yijing’s Chinese translation attributes a healing benefit to seeing these objects, thus explaining their placement in semipublic places; see Taishō 1447 1057b10–11: <hi rend="italic">能令明眼并療痔疾</hi>.</note></p>
                    </div>
                    <div type="chapter">
                        <head type="chapter">Awls, straps, and knives</head>
                        <p n="1.332">Another monk’s sandals were broken. He went to a shoemaker and when he arrived, he said, “My friend, stitch up my broken sandals and give them back to me!”</p>
                        <p n="1.333">The shoemaker thought, “Because the ascetic heirs of the Śākyan seek services without paying for them, I will procrastinate, and he will change his mind.” </p>
                        <p n="1.333">Thinking in this way, he said, “Noble one, I am busy, so come back tomorrow!” </p>
                        <p n="1.333">Although that monk went back to the shoemaker time and time again, the latter procrastinated.</p>
                        <p n="1.334">When his fellow monks saw that, they asked him, “Venerable one, is that the house that supplies you food<note place="end">“Supplies” or “prepares” food (Tib. <hi rend="italic">zas sbyor</hi>; Skt. none).</note> or the house of your kin?”</p>
                        <p n="1.335">He replied, “It is neither the house that supplies me food nor the house of my kin. Rather, my sandals were broken, so I said to the shoemaker, ‘Stitch them up and give them back to me!’ but he has procrastinated.”</p>
                        <p n="1.336">One of them said to him, “Have you not heard that truth-telling is a rarity in a shoemaker? However, since I have the skill, if the Blessed One allows it, I will stitch them up and give them back to you.”</p>
                        <p n="1.337">Monks reported this incident to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “If a monk has the skill, he may do the stitching while seated in a secluded spot where another will not lose faith if they see him.”<note place="end">The Sanskrit does not contain this last phrase, “where another will not lose faith if they see him” (Tib. <hi rend="italic">gzhan gyis mthong na mi dad par mi ’gyur ba</hi>).</note></p>
                        <p n="1.338">The first monk went to see his fellow monk and said to him, “Since the Blessed One has allowed it, stitch them up!”</p>
                        <p n="1.339">The other monk replied, “What do you think it should be stitched with?” </p>
                        <p n="1.339">“Well, for that you need an awl, a knife, and a strap.”</p>
                        <p n="1.340">Monks reported this incident to the Blessed One, and the Blessed One said, “If a monk has the skill, he may keep an awl and a strap. He should not carry a knife.”<note place="end">The Skt. <hi rend="italic">Chapter on Leather</hi> allows all three: <hi rend="italic">bhagavān āha / tasmād anujānāmi bhikṣuṇā ārā śastrakaṃ baddhikā ca dhārayitavyāḥ</hi>. In his digest of this, though, Guṇaprabha says that knives are disallowed, which is also stated in the Tibetan translation of <hi rend="italic">Chapter on Leather</hi> (Toh 4117, F.74.b): <hi rend="italic">de’i ched du smyung bu dang ko ba bcang bar bya’o//dra gri ni ma yin</hi>. The original Sanskrit of Guṇaprabha’s sūtra reads <hi rend="italic">dhārayet tadartham ārāṃ vardhrañ ca na śastrīm</hi>.</note></p>
                        <trailer>This concludes “The Chapter on Leather.”</trailer>
                    </div>
                </div>
            </div>
        </body>
        <back>
            <div type="notes">
                <head type="notes">Notes</head>
                <list type="abbreviations">
                    <head>Abbreviations</head>
                    <item><abbr>BHSD</abbr><expan>Edgerton, <hi rend="italic">Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Dictionary</hi></expan></item>
                    <item><abbr>Degé</abbr><expan>Degé Kangyur</expan></item>
                    <item><abbr>Divyāvadāna</abbr><expan>Cowell</expan></item>
                    <item><abbr>GBM</abbr><expan>III Dutt’s <hi rend="italic">Gilgit Buddhist Manuscripts, Vol. III</hi></expan></item>
                    <item><abbr>MW</abbr><expan>Monier-Williams, <hi rend="italic">A Sanskrit-English Dictionary</hi></expan></item>
                    <item><abbr>Stok</abbr><expan>Palace <hi rend="italic">Tog Palace manuscript of the Tibetan Kanjur</hi></expan></item>
                    <item><abbr>WTSS</abbr><expan><hi rend="italic">Wörterbuch der tibetischen Schriftsprache</hi></expan></item>
                </list>
            </div>
            <div type="listBibl">
                <head type="listBibl">Bibliography</head>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Kangyur and Tengyur Sources</head>
                    <bibl>ko lpags kyi gzhi (Carmavastu). Toh 1-5, Degé Kangyur vol. 1 (’dul ba, ka), folios 251.b–277.b.</bibl>
                    <bibl>ko lpags kyi gzhi (Carmavastu). ka’ ’gyur (dpe bsdur ma) [Comparative Edition of the Kangyur], krung go’i bod rig pa zhib ’jug ste gnas kyi bka’ bstan dpe sdur khang (The Tibetan Tripitaka Collation Bureau of the China Tibetology Research Center). 108 volumes. Beijing: krung go’i bod rig pa dpe skrun khang (China Tibetology Publishing House), 2006–9, vol. 1, pp. 585–644.</bibl>
                    <bibl>ko lpags kyi gzhi. Stog Palace Kangyur vol. 2 (’dul ba, ka) folios 359–389.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kalyāṇamitra. ’dul ba gzhi rgya cher ’grel ba (Vinaya­vastuṭīkā). Toh 4113, Degé Tengyur vol. 156 (’dul ba, tsu), folios 177.b–326.b.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Sanskrit Sources</head>
                    <bibl>Dutt, Nalinaksha, ed. Carmavastu of the Vinayavastvāgama of the Mūlasarvāstivādin. In Gilgit Manuscripts, Vol. III, part IV, pp. 159–210. Calcutta: Calcutta Oriental Press, 1950.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Tatelman, Joel. The Heavenly Exploits: Buddhist Biographies from the Divyāvadāna. New York: New York University Press, 2005.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Vira, Raghu and Lokesh Chandra. Gilgit Buddhist Manuscripts. Facsimile edition. New Delhi: 1959.</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Chinese Sources</head>
                    <bibl>Genben shuoyiqieyou bu pinaiye pigeshi 根本說一切有部毘奈耶皮革事 (Mūla­sarvāstivāda­vinaya Carmavastu), Taishō 1447. (CBETA; SAT).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pige fa 皮革法 (Carmavastu), in Shisong lü 十誦律 (Sarvāstivāda­vinaya), Taishō 1435. (CBETA; SAT).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pige fa 皮革法 (Carmavastu), in Wufen lü 五分律 (Mahīśāsaka­vinaya), Taishō 1421. (CBETA; SAT).</bibl>
                    <bibl>Pige jiandu 五分律 (Carmakhandhaka), in Sifen lü  四分律 (Dharma­guptaka­vinaya), Taishō 1428. (CBETA; SAT).</bibl>
                </div>
                <div type="section">
                    <head type="section">Secondary Sources</head>
                    <bibl>Allchin, F. Raymond and George Erdosy. The Archaeology of Early Historic South Asia : the Emergence of Cities and States. Cambridge University Press, 1995.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Anālayo, Bhikkhu. “Āgama and Aṅga in the Early Buddhist Oral Tradition.” Singaporean Journal of Buddhist Studies 3 (2016): 9–37.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Banerjee, Anukul Chandra. Sarvāstivāda Literature. World Press Private Ltd., 1979. Originally published in 1957.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bhattacarya, Dipak. “The Vedic Dṛti as Skin Float: AVP 2.19.” Journal of the Royal Asiatic Society 18, no. 3 (2008): 311–26.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Bronkhorst, Johannes. Buddhism in the Shadow of Brahmanism. Brill, 2011.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Buswell, Robert E., Jr., and Donald S. Lopez, Jr. The Princeton Dictionary of Buddhism. Princeton University Press, 2014.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Clarke, Shayne (2014). Vinaya Texts. The International Research Institute for Advanced Buddhology, Soka University.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Clarke, Shayne (2015). “Vinayas.” Brill’s Encyclopedia of Buddhism, edited by Jonathan Silk et al., vol. 1., Literature and Languages. Brill, pp. 60–87.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Clarke, Shayne (2016–17). “Lost in Tibet, found in Bhutan: the unique nature of the Mūlasarvāstivādin law code for nuns.” Buddhism, Law &amp; Society 2: 199–292.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Clarke, Shayne (2021). “On Some Curious Cases Where the Buddha Did Not Make a Rule: Palliative Care, Assisted Suicide, and Abortion in an Indian Buddhist Monastic Law Code.” International Journal of Buddhist Thought &amp; Culture 31 (1): 13–113. https://doi.org/10.16893/IJBTC.2021.06.30.1.13.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Collett, A. (2006). “List-based Formulae in the Avadānaśataka.” Buddhist Studies Review 23 (2): 155–85.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Cowell, Edward B., and Robert Alexander Neil, eds. The Divyāvadāna: A Collection of Early Buddhist Legends. Oriental Press, 1970. Originally published in 1886 by Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Edgerton, Franklin. Buddhist Hybrid Sanskrit Grammar and Dictionary. 2 vols. Vol. 2, Dictionary. Munshiram Manoharlal, 2004.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Erdosy, George (1988). Urbanisation in Early Historic India. BAR Publishing.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Erdosy, George (1995). “City States of North India and Pakistan at the Time of the Buddha.” In The Archaeology of Early Historic South Asia: the Emergence of Cities and States, edited by F. Raymond Allchin with George Erdosy, R. A. E. Coningham, D. K. Chakrabarti, and Bridget Allchin. Cambridge University Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Freiberger, Oliver. “Early Buddhism, Asceticism, and the Politics of the Middle Way.” In Asceticism and its Critics: Historical Accounts and Comparative Perspectives, edited by Oliver Freiberger. American Academy of Religion cultural criticism series. Oxford University Press, 2006.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Garfield, Jay. Buddhist Ethics: A Philosophical Exploration. Oxford University Press, 2021.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Heirman, Ann. 2016. Shoes in Buddhist Monasteries from India to China: From Practical Attire to Symbol. Acta Orientalia Academiae Scientiarum Hungaricae 69 (4): 411–39. .</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hirakawa, Akira. History of Indian Buddhism: From Śākyamuni To Early Mahāyāna. Edited and translated by Paul Groner. University of Hawai’i Press, 1990.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Hofinger, M. Le congrès du lac Anavatapta (vies des saints bouddhiques): extrait du Vinaya des Mūlasarvāstivādin Bhaiṣajyavastu. Vol. 1. Légendes des anciens (Sthavirāvadāna). Institut Orientaliste, 1982.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Horner, Isaline Blew. The Book of the Discipline, Volume IV. Luzac &amp; Company Ltd., 1962. First edition in 1951.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Jäschke, H. A Tibetan-English Dictionary. Curzon Press, 1998. Reprint of the edition published in London, 1881.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Kragh, U., ed. The Foundation for Yoga Practitioners: The Buddhist Yogācārabhūmi Treatise and Its Adaptation in India, East Asia, and Tibet. Harvard University, Department of South Asian Studies, 2013.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Lamotte, E. History of Indian Buddhism from the Origins to the Śaka Era. Translated by Sara Webb-Boin [sic]. Institut Orientaliste, 1988.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Law, Bimala Churn. Geography of Early Buddhism. Kegan Paul, Trench, Trubner &amp; Co., 1932. Ebook accessed at “Ancient Buddhist Texts,” January 2024.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Malalasekera, G. Dictionary of Pali Proper Names. Buddhist Publication Society, 1937. Accessed October 1, 2021.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Monier-Williams, M. A Sanskrit-English Dictionary. Clarendon Press, 1979.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Oldenberg, Hermann, trans. (1879). The Vinaya Piṭakaṃ: One of the Principal Buddhist Holy Scriptures in the Pali Language. Vol. 1. The Mahāvagga. London: Williams and Norgate.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Oldenberg, Hermann, trans. (1882) Vinaya Texts. Part 2. The Mahāvagga, 5–10; The Cullavagga, 1–3. In The Sacred Books of the East, vol. 17, edited by F. Max Müller. Clarendon Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Olivelle, Patrick (2007). “Explorations in the Early History of Dharmaśāstra.” In Between the Empires: Society in India 300 bce to 400 ce. Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Olivelle, Patrick. (2018). “Ascetics: vānaprastha, pravrajita.” In Hindu Law: A New History of Dharmaśāstra. Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Panglung, J. Die Erzählstoffe des Mūlasarvāstivāda-Vinaya analysiert auf Grund der tibetischen Übersetzung. Tokyo: Reiyukai Library, 1981.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Prebish, C. A Survey of Vinaya Literature. Jin Luen Publishing House, 1994.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Roach, Susan. “ ‘The Qualities of the Purified’: Attitudes Towards the Dhūtaguṇas in the Mūlasarvāstivāda-vinaya.” PhD diss., SOAS, University of London, 2020. [Available as PDF on academia.edu.]</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rotman, Andy (2008). Divine Stories: Divyāvadāna Part 1. Wisdom Publications, 2008.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Rotman, Andy (2021). Hungry Ghosts. Wisdom Publications, 2021.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schopen, Gregory. (2000) “Hierarchy and Housing in a Buddhist Monastic Code: A Translation of the Sanskrit text of the Śayanāsana­vastu of the Mūlasarvāstivāda-vinaya. Part One.” Journal of Buddhist Literature vol. 2: 92–196.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schopen, Gregory (2006). “A Well-Sanitized Shroud: Asceticism and Institutional Values in the Middle Period of Buddhist Monasticism.” In Between the Empires: Society in India 300 bce to 400 ce, edited by Patrick Olivelle. Oxford University Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schopen, Gregory (2014). “The Learned Monk as a Comic Figure: On Reading a Buddhist Vinaya as Indian Literature.” In Buddhist Nuns, Monks, and Other Worldly Matters. University of Hawai’i Press.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schopen, Gregory (2015). “The Fragrance of the Buddha, the Scent of Monuments, and the Odor of Images in Early India.” In Bulletin de l’Ecole française d’Extrême Orient, vol. 101: 11–30.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Schopen, Gregory (2022). “The Monk Mūlaphalguna and the Nuns: Biography as Criticism.” Hualin International Journal of Buddhist Studies 5.1: 313–33.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Skorupski, T. A Catalogue of the Stog Palace Kanjur. Tokyo: International Institute for Buddhist Studies, 1985.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Strauch, Ingo. “Lost in Translation? Canonical Languages and Linguistic Diversity of Early Versions of the Prātimokṣasūtra.” In Evolution of Scriptures, Formation of Canons: The Buddhist Case, edited by Orna Almogi. Indian and Tibetan Studies Series 13. Department of Indian and Tibetan Studies, Universität Hamburg, 2022.</bibl>
                    <bibl>Wörterbuch der tibetischen Schriftsprache. Verlag der Bayerischen Akademie der Wissenschaften in Kommission beim Verlag C. H. Beck, 2005.</bibl>
                </div>
            </div>
            <div type="glossary">
                <list type="glossary">
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49341">
                            <term type="translationMain">adulterer</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">pāradārika</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">byi bo</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The Sanskrit term pāradārika means one who has intercourse with “another’s wife.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-16210">
                            <term type="translationMain">Ajiravatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ajiravatī</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">a dzir ba ti</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A river at Śrāvastī.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-36853">
                            <term type="translationMain">alms seeker</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">piṇḍapātika</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">bsod snyoms pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of the ascetic practices known as dhūtaguṇas.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49342">
                            <term type="translationMain">ankle boot</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">nālāmbuja</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">lham mgul chad</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of footwear allowed for Buddhist monks in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41735">
                            <term type="translationMain">Anāthapiṇḍada</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">anāthapiṇḍada</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">mgon med zas sbyin</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41252">
                            <term type="translationMain">avadāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">avadāna</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rtogs pa brjod pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of twelve literary genres found in the Buddhist canon, avadānas (meaning “heroic acts” or “glorious exploits”) relate the past life actions which have culminated in a person’s present life attainments.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49343">
                            <term type="translationMain">awl</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ārā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">smyung bu</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Monks who know how to make and repair leather footwear are allowed to keep an awl, a strap, and, according to some sources, a knife to assist them in these tasks.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49376">
                            <term type="translationMain">Balasena</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">balasena</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">stobs kyi sde</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A wealthy householder, father of Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49344">
                            <term type="translationMain">bald-headed ascetic</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">muṇḍaka śramaṇaka</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">dge sbyong mgo reg</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A denigratory way to refer to a Buddhist monk.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-34957">
                            <term type="translationMain">Bamboo Grove</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">veṇuvana</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">’od ma’i tshal</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Site of the Kalandaka Sanctuary.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49345">
                            <term type="translationMain">bamboo-leaf sandal</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">vaṃśapatra­pādukā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">smyug lo’i mchil lham</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of footwear described in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49346">
                            <term type="translationMain">bed frame</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">maṃcaka</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">khri</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of furniture allowed for Buddhist monks mentioned in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49347">
                            <term type="translationMain">bodhi leaf</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">bodhi­paṭapatraka</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">byang chub kyi shing gi lo ma</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Sandals that resemble a bodhi leaf in shape. One of several types of footwear prohibited in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>, along with creaking sandals, tinkling sandals, sparkling sandals, ram’s horn sandals, multicolored sandals, and sandals that cost five coins.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49348">
                            <term type="translationMain">boot</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">muṇḍapūlā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">lham yu’u thung</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of footwear allowed for Buddhist monks in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-42602">
                            <term type="translationMain">Brahmā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">brahmā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">tshangs pa</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-3996">
                            <term type="translationMain">breach</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">sātisāra</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">’gal tshabs can</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The term “breach” does not uniquely correspond to any of the five types of offense a monk should avoid. Instead, context determines which class of offense any specific breach belongs to. See Clarke 2021 p, 71 n. 80.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49349">
                            <term type="translationMain">buskin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">maṇḍapūlā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">lham sgro gu can</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A calf- or thigh-high boot allowed for monks living in snowy regions. One of several types of footwear allowed for Buddhist monks in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-31145">
                            <term type="translationMain">Campā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">campā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">tsam pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Ancient capital of Aṅga.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49352">
                            <term type="translationMain">cowhide</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gocarman</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ba’i ko ba</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of leather or hide used in ground-spreads and ground-spread covers in the frontier country of Aśmaka.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49353">
                            <term type="translationMain">creaking</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">hinihināyamānā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">thrig thrig</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Perhaps onomatopoeic. Monks are not allowed to wear creaking sandals. One of several types of footwear prohibited in The Chapter on Leather, along with tinkling sandals, sparkling sandals, ram’s horn sandals, sandals like a bodhi leaf, multicolored sandals, and sandals that cost five coins.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49354">
                            <term type="translationMain">deerskin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">mṛgacarman</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ri dgas kyi pags pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of leather or hide used in ground-spreads and ground-spread covers in the frontier country of Aśmaka.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-1675">
                            <term type="translationMain">dhyāna</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">dhyāna</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">bsam gtan</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>In the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya, the term dhyāna is used in a general sense to mean “meditation.” Note, however, that in Buddhist literature dhyāna often refers to specific meditative states involving increasing detachment from both sensory and mental objects.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-10775">
                            <term type="translationMain">Dāsaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">dāsaka</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">bran</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>An attendant to Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, whose name means “servant.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-1172">
                            <term type="translationMain">fellow brahmacārin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">sabrahmacārin</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">tshangs pa mtshungs par spyod pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>In a Buddhist context, the term brahman or “holy” refers to nirvāṇa, and hence a Buddhist brahmacārin is a monk engaged in or living the “holy life.” The “holy life” is generally understood to mean a “life of celibacy” which, in Buddhist usage, implies also a life that leads to nirvāṇa. Here, a “fellow brahmacārin” would thus be a fellow monk.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49371">
                            <term type="translationMain">focused his recollection</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">pratimukham smṛtim upasthāpya</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">dgongs pa mngon du bzhag ste</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>To collect one’s attention and direct it to meditation.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49355">
                            <term type="translationMain">four āgamas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">āgamacatuṣtaya</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">lung gzhi</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The Mūlasarvāstivādin tradition grouped the Buddha’s early sūtra discourses into four divisions, or āgama (Tib. mdo sde’i lung sde bzhi): the Dīrghāgama (Tib. lung ring po), the Madhyamāgama (Tib. lung bar ma), the Ekottarikāgama (Tib. lung gcig las ’phros pa), and the Saṃyuktāgama (Tib. lung dag ldan/yang dar par ldan pa’i lung). They are more familiar to many English-speaking Buddhists through the translations of their Pali correlates: the Dīgha Nikāya, Majjhima Nikāya, Aṅguttara Nikāya, and the Samyutta Nikāya, for which see the Wisdom Publications titles: The Long Discourses of the Buddha, The Middle-Length Discourses of the Buddha, The Numerical Discourses of the Buddha, and The Connected Discourses of the Buddha, respectively.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49382">
                            <term type="translationMain">frontier country of Aśmaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">aśmāparāntako janapadaḥ</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rdo can zhes bya ba’i yul gyi mtha’</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The Sanskrit Chapter on Leather gives this location first in the probably erroneous form aśmakana­garāntaka (Tib. F.251.b rdo can zhes bya ba’i yul gyi mtha’ na), or “border town of Aśma.” In the second case, the probably correct Sanskrit reads aśmāparāntakeṣu jana­padeṣu or “in the frontier land of Aśma” (the Tibetan translation is identical to the previous instance: rdo can zhes bya ba’i yul gyi mtha’ na). According to Edgerton, the Skt. aparāntaka (p. 44, col. 2) can refer specifically to the country of Aparānta or more generally to the western border (i.e., in present-day Maharashtra). In his translation of the parallel passages in the Divyāvadāna, Rotman (2008: p. 392, n. 85) gives “region of Aśmāparāntaka,” which he explains to be a conjunct of Aparānta (as in “the country of…”) and Aśma (a.k.a. Aśmaka, Aśvaka, Pali Assaka, the latter of which is also in present-day Maharashtra). The Tibetan translation supports Rotman’s suggestion to take Aśma to be the name of a specific region in the western lands, rendered in Tibetan as rdo can. Thus, here, we have elected to translate this phrase in both instances as “the frontier country of Aśmaka.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41097">
                            <term type="translationMain">fruit of non-returning</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">anāgāmiphala</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">phyir mi ’ong ba’i ’bras bu</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Third stage on the path to becoming an arhat.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41096">
                            <term type="translationMain">fruit of once-returning</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">sakṛdāgāmi­phala</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">lan gcig phyir ’ong ba’i ’bras bu</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Second stage on the path to becoming an arhat.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41098">
                            <term type="translationMain">fruit of stream entry</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">srota-āpattiphala</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rgyun du zhugs pa’i ’bras bu</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>First stage on the path to becoming an arhat.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-16">
                            <term type="translationMain">gandharva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gandharva</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">dri za</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-33538">
                            <term type="translationMain">garden</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">maṇḍalavāṭa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">’khor gyi khyams</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>This is one of many related terms for an assembly hall that appear in the Kangyur and Tengyur, such as (1) “meditation residence” or “meditation hall” (Tib. spong khang; Skt. prahāṇaśāla), (2) “multistoried structure” (Tib. khang pa rtseg ma’i khyams; Skt. kūṭāgāraśālā), (3) “temple” or “hall” (various Tib., e.g. khyams and khang bzangs; Skt. prāsāda), (4) “steps” (Tib. bang rim; Skt. pariṣaṇḍā), and (5) “courtyard” or “terrace” (Tib. ’khor gyi khyams; Skt. maṇḍalavāṭa).</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49356">
                            <term type="translationMain">goatskin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">chāgacarman</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ra’i pags pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of leather or hide used in ground-spreads and ground-spread covers in the frontier country of Aśmaka.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-46886">
                            <term type="translationMain">ground-spread</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">āstaraṇa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gding ba</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>In his Chinese translation of <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>, Yijing (T 1447, 1052b12) gives a single term, wo ju 臥具 where the Sanskrit from Gilgit gives both āstaraṇa or “ground-spread” and pratyāstaraṇa or “ground-spread cover.” Ground-spreads and ground-spread covers were laid out on the ground or on furniture so that monks could sit or sleep comfortably and without damaging the community’s furniture.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-35442">
                            <term type="translationMain">group of six</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ṣaḍvargika</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">drug sde rnams</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A group of monks led by Nanda and Upananda who are consistently portrayed as indulgent and attached to material comforts. See the introduction to The Chapter on Leather.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-42033">
                            <term type="translationMain">Heaven of the Thirty-Three</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">trāyastriṃśa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">sum bcu rtsa gsum pa’i gnas</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-37341">
                            <term type="translationMain">holy life</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">brahmacarya</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">tshangs par spyod pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>In a Buddhist context, the term brahman or “holy” refers to nirvāṇa, and hence, for a Buddhist, the “holy life” means living a life conducive to nirvāṇa, generally implying celibacy.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-35334">
                            <term type="translationMain">hungry ghost</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">preta</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">yi dags</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41965">
                            <term type="translationMain">Indra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">indra</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">dbang po</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-7982">
                            <term type="translationMain">Isle of Jewels</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ratnadvīpa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rin po che’i gling</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The name of an island or group of islands where precious stones and gems were extraordinarily plentiful and easily obtained.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-42029">
                            <term type="translationMain">Jambudvīpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">jambudvīpa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">’dzam bu’i gling</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-3853">
                            <term type="translationMain">Kalandaka Sanctuary</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kalandakanivāsa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ka lan da ka gnas</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>This site derives its names from the birds whose chirping awoke King Bimbisāra and saved him from the bite of a deadly snake. In gratitude, the king forbade harming the birds in this park. The Sanskrit Chapter on a Schism in the Saṅgha identifies the kalandaka as a bird in its telling of the site’s origins (Toh 1-17, F.77.b–78.a). There, the Sanskrit glosses the site’s name as “the winged ones known as ‘kalandaka’ ”: kalandakā nāma pakṣiṇaḥ) while the Tibetan appends the word for “bird” (Tib. bya) to a transliteration of kalandaka, in effect designating the kalandaka a type of bird (Toh 1-17 F.77.b): bya ka lan ka zhes bya ba de rnams kyis). The Skt. pakṣin, “winged one,” is a common poetic synonym for “bird.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-44093">
                            <term type="translationMain">Kapilavastu</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kapilavastu</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ser skya</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The Śākyan capital, home of the Bodhisattva before his renunciation.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-40303">
                            <term type="translationMain">Kośala</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kośala</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ko sa la</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Prasenajit’s kingdom and later Virūḍhaka’s.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41976">
                            <term type="translationMain">Kubera</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kubera</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">lus ngan</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-1127">
                            <term type="translationMain">kulattha peas</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kulattha</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">mon sran</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Latin: Dolichos uniflorus (MW), synonymous with Macrotyloma uniflorum or “horse gram.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-46916">
                            <term type="translationMain">Kārtika</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kārtika</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ston zla ’bring po</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Late October/Early November.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41972">
                            <term type="translationMain">Kāśyapa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kāśyapa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">’od srung</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-16453">
                            <term type="translationMain">Kṛkin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kṛkin</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kr-i kI</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>King of Vārāṇasī during the time of the Buddha Kāśyapa.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49357">
                            <term type="translationMain">leather sandal</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">carmapādukā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ko ba’i mchil lham</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of footwear allowed for Buddhist monks in The Chapter on Leather.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-43689">
                            <term type="translationMain">Mahākātyāyana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">mahākātyāyana</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kA tyA ya na chen po</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-32632">
                            <term type="translationMain">mattress</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">śayyā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">mal stan</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The Sanskrit terms śayyā and śayanāsana were rendered into Tibetan with both mal cha and mal stan.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-36859">
                            <term type="translationMain">monastery</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">vihāra</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gtsug lag khang</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>In <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>, the Sanskrit term vihāra is used to refer to individual buildings in a monastic compound.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49359">
                            <term type="translationMain">muñja grass sandal</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">muñjapādukā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rtswa mun dza’i mchil lham</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of footwear allowed for Buddhist monks in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-46750">
                            <term type="translationMain">mātṛkā</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">mātṛkā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ma mo</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>In the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya, mātṛkā (Tib. ma mo, Eng. “mother”) is frequently used as a name for the Basket of Abhidharma.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41993">
                            <term type="translationMain">Nanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">nanda</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">dga’ bo</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-1784">
                            <term type="translationMain">Nepal</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">Naivāla</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">bal yul</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Although the name “Nepal” derives from Naivāla (also given as Naipāla and Nepāla), the ancient Nepāla would probably not extend beyond the Kathmandu Valley.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-2">
                            <term type="translationMain">nāga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">nāga</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">klu</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-4093">
                            <term type="translationMain">offense requiring forfeiture</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">pāyattika</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">spang ba’i ltung byed</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One type of offense Buddhist monks must avoid. This type of offense stems from the monk possessing material goods, such as cloth, in excess of allowance.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-5553">
                            <term type="translationMain">one thus gone</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">tathāgata</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">de bzhin gshegs pa</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-16876">
                            <term type="translationMain">Passing to the Farther Shore</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">Pārāyaṇa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">pha rol ’gro byed</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A lost verse text, which was possibly a Mūlasarvāstivādin counterpart of the Pārāyanavagga of the Suttanipāta in the Pāli canon and thought to be included in the Kṣudrakavastu.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-9367">
                            <term type="translationMain">Pilindavatsa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">pilindavatsa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">pi lin da’i bu</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-40255">
                            <term type="translationMain">Prasenajit</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">prasenajit</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gsal rgyal</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-44205">
                            <term type="translationMain">Prince Jeta’s Grove, Anāthapiṇḍada’s Park</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">jetavanam anāthapiṇḍadasyārāmaḥ</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rgyal rgyal byed kyi tshal mgon med zas sbyin gyi kun dga’ ra ba</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49383">
                            <term type="translationMain">Puṇḍrakakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">puṇḍrakakṣa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">li kha ra tshang tshing</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A forest to the east, beyond which the Buddha designated “border regions.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-45487">
                            <term type="translationMain">Puṇḍravardhana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">puṇḍravardhana</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">li kha ra shing ’phel</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A town to the east, adjacent to the border forest of Puṇḍrakakṣa.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-11892">
                            <term type="translationMain">Pālaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">pālaka</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">skyong ba</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>An attendant to Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa, whose name means “protector.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49360">
                            <term type="translationMain">ram’s horn</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">meṇḍaviṣānikā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">lug ru</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Monks are not allowed to wear ram’s horn. One of several types of footwear prohibited in The Chapter on Leather, along with creaking sandals, tinkling sandals, sparkling sandals, sandals like a bodhi leaf, multicolored sandals, and sandals that cost five coins.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49361">
                            <term type="translationMain">rope sandal</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rajjupādukā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">srad bu’i mchil lham</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of footwear allowed for Buddhist monks in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-42024">
                            <term type="translationMain">Rājagṛha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rājagṛha</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rgyal po’i khab</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49362">
                            <term type="translationMain">sandal</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">upānahā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">mchil lham</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of footwear allowed for Buddhist monks in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49363">
                            <term type="translationMain">seat</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">pīṭha</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">khri’u</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of furniture allowed for Buddhist monks.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49374">
                            <term type="translationMain">seats made of wool</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">eraka</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">bal stan</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of material used in ground-spreads and ground-spread covers in the Buddhist heartland of ancient India.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49350">
                            <term type="translationMain">seats of cotton</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">janduraka</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">srin bal gyi stan</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of material used in ground-spreads and ground-spread covers in the Buddhist heartland of ancient India.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49351">
                            <term type="translationMain">seats of cotton-wool mix</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">manduraka</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ras bal gyi stan</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of material used in ground-spreads and ground-spread covers in the Buddhist heartland of ancient India.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49537">
                            <term type="translationMain">seats of tree bark</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">meraka</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of material used in ground-spreads and ground-spread covers in the Buddhist heartland of ancient India.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-16879">
                            <term type="translationMain">Seeing the Truth</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">Satyadṛś</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">bden pa mthong ba</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A lost verse text possibly included in the Kṣudrakavastu.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49364">
                            <term type="translationMain">sheepskin</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ajacarman</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">lug gi pags pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of leather or hide used in ground-spreads and ground-spread covers in the frontier country of Aśmaka.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49365">
                            <term type="translationMain">shoemaker</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">carmakāra</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">lham mkhan</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A cobbler or maker of shoes.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49366">
                            <term type="translationMain">sparkling</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">chem chem</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Monks are not allowed to wear “sparkling” footwear. One of several types of footwear prohibited in The Chapter on Leather, along with creaking sandals, tinkling sandals, ram’s horn sandals, sandals like a bodhi leaf, multicolored sandals, and sandals that cost five coins. One of several types of footwear described in The Chapter on Leather is said to “sparkle,” though the exact meaning of this in unclear and no Sanskrit is extant for this term.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49385">
                            <term type="translationMain">Sthūṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">sthūṇa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ka ba</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A brahmin town to the west, beyond which, along with the adjacent town of Upasthūṇa, the Buddha designated “border regions.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49367">
                            <term type="translationMain">strap</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">baddhikā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">’breng bu</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A fastener used for shoes.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-43556">
                            <term type="translationMain">stūpa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">stūpa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">mchod rten</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49379">
                            <term type="translationMain">Sujāta</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">sujāta</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">legs skyes</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Son and successor of King Kṛkin, who neglects a stūpa built by his father for the relics of the Buddha Kāśyapa.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49387">
                            <term type="translationMain">Sūtras Concerning the Goal</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">Artha­vargīyāṇi sūtrāṇi</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">don gyi tshoms kyi mdo sde dag</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A lost verse text possibly included in the Kṣudrakavastu.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-324">
                            <term type="translationMain">The Inspired Utterances</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">udāna</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ched du brjod pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of twelve literary genres found in the Buddhist canon. Inspired utterances generally begin with a brief narrative explaining the circumstances that inspired the verses spoken by the Buddha.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-16881">
                            <term type="translationMain">The Verses of the Elder Nuns</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">Sthavirīgāthā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gnas brtan ma’i tshigs su bcad pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A lost verse text possibly included in the Kṣudrakavastu.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-16880">
                            <term type="translationMain">The Verses of the Elders</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">Sthaviragāthā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gnas brtan gyi tshigs su bcad pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A lost verse text possibly included in the Kṣudrakavastu.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-16875">
                            <term type="translationMain">The Verses of the Sage</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">Munigāthā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">thub pa’i tshigs su bcad pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A lost verse text possibly included in the Kṣudrakavastu.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-16877">
                            <term type="translationMain">The Verses of Śaila</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">Śailagāthā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ri gnas kyi tshigs su bcad pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A verse text included in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Medicines</hi> -.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41726">
                            <term type="translationMain">three realms</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">traidhātuka</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">khams gsum</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The desire realm, form realm, and formless realm.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49358">
                            <term type="translationMain">three-robe practice</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">traicīvarika</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">chos gos gsum pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of the ascetic practices known as dhūtaguṇas.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49368">
                            <term type="translationMain">tinkling</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kiṇikiṇāyamānā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">tshig tshig</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Perhaps onomatopoeic. Monks are not allowed to wear footwear made with tinkling sandals. One of several types of footwear prohibited in The Chapter on Leather, along with creaking sandals, sparkling sandals, ram’s horn sandals, sandals like a bodhi leaf, multicolored sandals, and sandals that cost five coins.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41066">
                            <term type="translationMain">training precepts</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">śikṣāpada</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">bslab pa’i gzhi rnams</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The rules that Buddhist monastics have pledged to uphold.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-7574">
                            <term type="translationMain">Tripiṭaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">tripiṭaka</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">sde snod gsum</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The Buddha’s teachings have traditionally been grouped by subject matter into three classes or “baskets”: the basket of Sūtra or “discourses”; the basket of Vinaya or “monastic discipline”; and the basket of Abhidharma, which examines the philosophical ideas and terms used in the discourses.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-43757">
                            <term type="translationMain">udumbara tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">udumbara</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">u dum bA ra</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Ficus glomerata. A fig tree in which the flower is concealed within the fruit. As the flower of the udumbara tree remains unseen, it has come to symbolize extreme rarity in classical Indian literature.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41497">
                            <term type="translationMain">universal monarch</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">cakravartin</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">’khor los sgyur ba’i rgyal po</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-19105">
                            <term type="translationMain">Upananda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">upananda</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">nye dga’</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49386">
                            <term type="translationMain">Upasthūṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">upasthūṇa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">nye ba’i ka ba</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A brahmin town to the west, beyond which, along with the adjacent town of Sthūṇa, the Buddha designated “border regions.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-16635">
                            <term type="translationMain">Upendra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">upendra</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">nye dbang po</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A name for Viṣṇu or Kṛṣṇa</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-42019">
                            <term type="translationMain">Upāli</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">upāli</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">nye ba ’khor</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-16779">
                            <term type="translationMain">Uśīragiri</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">uśīragiri</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">u shi ri’i ri</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A mountain to the north, beyond which the Buddha designated “border regions.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-43648">
                            <term type="translationMain">Vaiśravaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">vaiśravaṇa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rnam thos kyi bu</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-43561">
                            <term type="translationMain">Vaiśālī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">Vaiśālī</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">yangs pa can</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The ancient capital of the Licchavi republic. The Buddha visited this city several times during his lifetime. It is perhaps most famous as the location where, on different occasions, he cured a plague, admitted the first nuns into the Buddhist order, was offered a bowl of honey by monkeys, and announced his parinirvāṇa three months prior to his departure..</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-31673">
                            <term type="translationMain">Varuṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">varuṇa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">chu lha</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49375">
                            <term type="translationMain">Vaḍra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">vaḍra</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">chen po</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>King Prasenajit’s keeper of cattle.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-4068">
                            <term type="translationMain">vinaya holder</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">vinayadhara</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">’dul ba ’dzin pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A “vinaya holder” is term that denotes expertise in the canonical Vinaya. Such a vinaya holder is expected to know not only the Prātimokṣa Sūtra but also the Vinayavibhaṅga, in which the monks' rules are explained, and the monastic rites described in the Vinayavastu.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49380">
                            <term type="translationMain">Virūḍhaka</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">virūḍhaka</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">’phags skyes po</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-42025">
                            <term type="translationMain">Vulture Peak Mountain</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gṛdhrakūṭa­parvata</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">bya rgod kyi phung po ri</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-43670">
                            <term type="translationMain">Vārāṇasī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">vārāṇasī</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">bA rA Na sI</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49381">
                            <term type="translationMain">Vāsava</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">vāsava</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gnas pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A village in the kingdom of Kāśī, whose capital city was Vārāṇasī.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-15540">
                            <term type="translationMain">walkway</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">caṅkrama</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">’chag sa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>An area set aside within a monastery where monks may practice walking meditation.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49369">
                            <term type="translationMain">with a single lining</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ekapalāśikā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rim gcig pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of footwear allowed for Buddhist monks in The Chapter on Leather.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49370">
                            <term type="translationMain">with heel covers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rting pa sbu bu can</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of footwear allowed for Buddhist monks in The Chapter on Leather.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49372">
                            <term type="translationMain">with toe covers</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">puṭāpuṭī</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rtse mo sbu bu can</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of footwear allowed for Buddhist monks in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49373">
                            <term type="translationMain">wooden sandal</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kāṣṭhapādukā</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">shing gi mchil lham</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>One of several types of footwear allowed for Buddhist monks in <hi rend="italic">The Chapter on Leather</hi>.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-35785">
                            <term type="translationMain">yakṣa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">yakṣa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gnod sbyin</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-844">
                            <term type="translationMain">yoga</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">yoga</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">rnal ’byor</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Nowadays, yoga is generally associated with haṭhayoga or one of its derivatives, which emphasize bodily postures and breath control. But the aṣṭāṅgayoga or “eight-limbed yoga” taught by Patañjali in the Yogasūtra includes much more, such as vows, social duties, and obligations. Here, in the Mūlasarvāstivāda Vinaya, yoga refers to the seated practice of meditation.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-40469">
                            <term type="translationMain">Ānanda</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">ānanda</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">kun dga’ bo</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-2613">
                            <term type="translationMain">Āṣāḍha</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">āṣāḍha</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">dbyar zla ’bring po</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Late June/early July.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-42004">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śakra</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">śakra</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">brgya byin</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49384">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śarāvatī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">śarāvatī</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">’dam bu can</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A town and also a river to the south, beyond which the Buddha designated “border regions.”</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-43482">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śitavana</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">śītavana</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">bsil ba’i tshal</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A famous charnel ground near Bodh Gaya.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-35804">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śiva</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">śiva</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">zhi ba</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-33258">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śravaṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">śravaṇa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gro bzhin</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Name of a constellation.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49377">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śroṇa Koṭīkarṇa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">śroṇaḥ koṭīkarṇah</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gro bzhin skyes rna ba bye ba ri</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>Son of the wealthy householder Balasena, whose name means “born under Śravaṇa with an ear worth ten million.” His strange encounters on a lengthy sea voyage provide lessons in karmic cause and effect, and he eventually becomes an arhat disciple of the Buddha.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-49378">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śroṇa Koṭīviṃśa</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">śroṇa koṭīviṃśa</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">gro bzhin skyes bye ba nyi shu pa</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>The privileged son of a wealthy merchant who goes forth as a monk under the Buddha. The story of his extreme determination in walking meditation provides the background for the Buddha allowing his monks single-lining sandals.</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-41892">
                            <term type="translationMain">Śrāvastī</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">śrāvastī</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">mnyan yod</hi></term>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <gloss type="term" n="entity-43750">
                            <term type="translationMain">śāla tree</term>
                            <term xml:lang="Sa-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">śāla</hi></term>
                            <term xml:lang="Bo-Ltn"><hi rend="italic">shing sA la</hi></term>
                            <note type="definition">
                                <p>A tree native to the Indian subcontinent, commonly said to be the type of tree under which the Buddha was born and passed away. Lat. Shorea robusta</p>
                            </note>
                        </gloss>
                    </item>
                </list>
            </div>
        </back>
    </text>
</TEI>
